<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration concerning the needfulnesse of peace to be made in Fraunce and the means for the making of the same: exhibited to the most Christian king, Henrie the second of that name, King of Fraunce and Polande, vpon two edictes, put forth by his Maiestie, the one the tenth of September, the other the thirtenth of October. Anno. 1574. Translated out of Frenche by G. H. Esquire.</title>
            <title>Remonstrance au roy ... sur le faict des deux edicts ... touchant la necessité de paix &amp; moyens de la faire. English</title>
            <author>Gentillet, Innocent, ca. 1535-ca. 1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112648</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847894</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847894</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12958</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12958)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration concerning the needfulnesse of peace to be made in Fraunce and the means for the making of the same: exhibited to the most Christian king, Henrie the second of that name, King of Fraunce and Polande, vpon two edictes, put forth by his Maiestie, the one the tenth of September, the other the thirtenth of October. Anno. 1574. Translated out of Frenche by G. H. Esquire.</title>
                  <title>Remonstrance au roy ... sur le faict des deux edicts ... touchant la necessité de paix &amp; moyens de la faire. English</title>
                  <author>Gentillet, Innocent, ca. 1535-ca. 1595.</author>
                  <author>Harte, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Bynneman, for Raufe Newberie, dwelling in Fleetstreat, a little aboue the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1575]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G. H. = George Harte.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Gentillet, Innocent.  Remonstrance au roy .. sur le faict des deux edicts .. touchant la necessité de paix &amp; moyens de la faire.</note>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Title page has error; should be "Henrie the third"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par]⁴ A-I K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Henry III, 1574-1589 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning the need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of peace to be made in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and the means for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſame: exhibited to the moſt Chriſtian king, Henrie the ſecond of that name, King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,</hi> vpon two Edictes, put forth by his Maieſtie, the one the tenth of September, the other the thirtenth of October. Anno. 1574.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Frenche by <hi>G. H.</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London</hi> by Henrie Bynneman, for Raufe Newberie, dwelling in Fleetſtreat, a little aboue the Conduit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:3"/>
            <head>¶ To the right worſhipfull his eſpeciall good father Sir Pearciuall Hart Knight, one of the Sewars, and Knight Harbinger to hir Maieſtie: his humble and obedient ſonne G. H. wiſheth health and long lyfe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now (Syr) long time ſince I not onely deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but fully de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>termined, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of my dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you, by ſome peece of my trauell, in this preſent kinde of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe. The bringing whereof to paſſe, although I haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſought by peruſing many bookes: yet could
<pb facs="tcp:12958:4"/> I not light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any to anſwere my contentment (which ſtood alwayes on the choyce of ſome ſuch matter, as J thought myght best like you) vntil there chanced into my hands this little frenche aduertiſement: The which I had no ſoner read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but by and by there was kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in me a certaine deſirouſneſſe to take it in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, partly for the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therof, which caryeth great cauſe of likelyhoode to pleaſe the reader in generall: but chiefly for my perticular purpoſe to delight you, whom I know to haue a ſpecial inclination to heare and reade the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:4"/> diſcourſes of the frenche affayres, bycauſe you youre ſelfe in youre yong dais, hauing ſerued the kings Grandfather <hi>Francis</hi> of Valoys, in his Courte, and trauayled that countrey, haue had good occaſion to be acquainted with the cuſtoms thereof, and with the nature of the people there. And I doubte not but it will like you ſo much the better, for the varietie of foraine histories, applyed most aptly to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the preſent mater, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is, I ſay not poudered or fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but fraughted. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, althoughe my liking of the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:5"/> worke did hale forward my labour to the tranſlating thereof: yet I must needes ſay, that after I was ſomewhat entred thereinto, ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes there ſtoode vp ſuch a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of doubts, and ſo huge a heape of imperfections to withstand me, as had not my deſire to pleaſure you preuayled againste all thoſe ſtoppes and ſtayes: my trauell and deuotion therein had lyen in the dust, before my race had halfe bin runne. But yet notwithstandyng, the reaſons aforeſayd, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire I had to do the thing, and the delight I tooke in doing it, wrought
<pb facs="tcp:12958:5"/> ſuch perſuaſion and incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in me, and did ſo keepe me ſtill in breath, as I neuer gaue it ouer, till J had turned it into Engliſhe, in ſuche ſorte, as you my good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may nowe voucheſafe to ſee: to whome, J moste humbly preſent it as a newyeeres gift. Therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hartely wiſhing, that your ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt zeale towardes all wiſe, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and vertuous proceedynges, (whereof neereneſſe in bloud for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth me to ſpeak according ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to your deſert, or to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, deſire, and duetie) may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, to Gods glory &amp; the profit
<pb facs="tcp:12958:6"/> of your countrey. And the ſame God proſper you and all youre do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, and bleſſe you with manye moe newe yeeres, to the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of your owne harts deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>This first of Ianuary .1575.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your humble and obedient ſonne <hi>George Harte.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="edict">
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:6"/>
            <head>¶ The fyrſte Edicte the tenth of December, of the wil and intent of the most Christian King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Poland, Henry</hi> of <hi>Valoys,</hi> the third of that name.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enry</hi> by the grace of God Kyng of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> To all that ſhall ſee and reade this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Edict, greting. The brotherly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie whyche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hathe bene mutually betweene our late moſt honorable Lord and brother king <hi>Charles,</hi> (whoſe ſoule God pardone) and vs, and the naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and duetie whiche we haue to the conſeruation and quietneſſe of thys realme, hathe heretofore not only made vs mindfull of the welfare of our ſayde late Lorde and brother, and of his ſubiects: but alſo inforced vs to neglect our owne commodities, and
<pb facs="tcp:12958:7"/> to participate the care &amp; trauell of managing all affayres, as wel publike as priuate, and as well of wars as of peace: in which we haue willingly imployed, not only al our means, but alſo our own proper perſon, as appereth by diuers encounters &amp; battailes, which God by his holy grace hath alwais fauored accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right &amp; equitie of the cauſe which we defend. Whereas notwithſtanding it is moſt certain &amp; euident, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſes in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> caſe ſo happening as wel on the one part as on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, did altogether tend to the diminiſhing &amp; weakning of the forces of the realme. Our ſayde late brother knowing this, had at ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times aſſayed to qualifie the ſharpneſſe of that inconuenience, by benignitie and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, indeuouring to bryng agayne the hartes of his ſubiects to their due obedience by gentleneſſe, and to reconcile their willes to good vnitie and concorde, whiche were at oddes before, ſpecially the yeere paſſed when I was his Liefetenant generall before <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel:</hi> we following his mind and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement by the aduice and counſell of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Lords &amp; notable perſons, which at that time wer with vs, did the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again accept y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:12958:7"/> means of pacification, which we thought moſt meeteſt, as the thing which we ſpecially deſired, to be firme &amp; durable, knowing that the moſt part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubiects of the realme, had ſufficiently tried, felt, &amp; proued the miſeries &amp; calamities which ciuil &amp; inwarde war brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very cauſe, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope wherof, we tooke our iourney into <hi>Polande,</hi> whither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtates of the countrey (that alittle before had elected vs for their king) did call vs: wheras if we had thought that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warres ſhuld haue ſeaſed &amp; reſted ſo ſhort a time, we had not aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doned our ſaid lord &amp; brother, nor yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realm. But rather we wold haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; defence thereof, aboue al aduanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or perticular benefite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could touch vs or apertain vnto vs. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſome being ſeduced by euill councel, haue vnder diuers prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, renued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troubles and entred again into armes. Wherby it is come to paſſe that the realme is immediatly falne into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame malady of whiche it was but newly crept out, &amp; the means y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had bin atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted for the redreſſe thereof, brought not the fruite that was looked for, and deſired. Nowe for aſmuche as it is the duetie of a good king, as well as of a good father and
<pb facs="tcp:12958:8"/> paſtor, to ſtrayne him ſelfe to the vttermoſt of his power, and to imploy all his doyngs to the benefyte and preſeruation of thoſe whome God hathe put vnder hys charge, ſpecially at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of hys raigne. And ſeeing that it hath pleaſed the deuine boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to call vs to the rule and gouernment of this realme: We haue thought good, fyrſt of all to proue all meanes poſſible to bryng our ſubiectes agayne to the righte way by gentle meanes, that they may lyue peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably one with another in good vnitie and concord, and yeld vs the obedience whiche by all right they ought to do, as the thing whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che euery man of his owne parte ought of right to deſire and procure. Therefore to the intent that all men may vnderſtand our wil and meaning, which tendeth to nothing but the benefyte and comfort of the Realme and our ſubiects: We haue ſayd and declared, and do ſay and declare, that all thoſe whiche heretofore haue riſen and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> armes againſt our late Lorde and brother the king laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, and againſt his authoritie and ours, or haue abſented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Realm, withdrawing them into ſtrange countries
<pb facs="tcp:12958:8"/> without our leaue, and at this preſent will lay a part armes, giue ouer the practiſes of warre, returne home into their houſes, leaue vp and put into our obeyſance the townes which they hold and occupy, and do as good and loyall ſubiects ought to do to their king and ſoueraigne Prince: they ſhall fynde vs diſpoſed and ready to admit and receyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into our good grace, with intention and will to intreate them well, forgetting the former things, and prouiding that neyther preſente nor to come, any of thoſe of what quality degree or condition ſo euer they be, or for any cauſe that may bee pretended to haue bin done by them during the troubles, ſhall any way be diſquieted, moleſted, or ſif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by vs or our officers, eyther in their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, goodes, or honors, but ſhall lyue in all aſſurance, reſt, and tranquilitie, both they, theyr families, and poſterities: aſſuring them that if they will come or ſende to vs to thys ende, they ſhall do it with all ſuretie by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of theſe preſents, whiche ſhall ſerue them for ſafeconduit, howbeit ſo as in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming towardes vs, they take ſafeconduites and paſports of the gouernours and Liefete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants
<pb facs="tcp:12958:9"/> of the prouinces by which they paſſe, whom we authoriſe &amp; enioyn to do ſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out refuſall or let, commanding all gouernours &amp; captaines of places iuſticers &amp; officers, Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refs of towns, and other our ſubiectes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their duties to let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſe in all ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards vs, without giuing or ſuffering to be giuen, any diſturbance, moleſtation, or impeachme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And if any of them be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to receiue &amp; accept this our fauour, &amp; to vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodneſſe &amp; clemencie which we offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather wil perſeuer in their euil inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; purpoſes: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are we fully reſolued to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy al the means which God hath put into our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, to repreſſe their inſolencies, and to bring their malapertneſſe &amp; raſhneſſe to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: wherin we hope &amp; do promiſe our ſelfs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god (who knoweth our intent) wil of his gracious goodnes fauour &amp; ayd vs, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authoritie which we acknowledge our ſelues to hold of him: And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therwithal our good and loyal ſubiects wil not forget their duties &amp; allegea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which they haue alwayes borne vs, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end therfore the rather to put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme in quietneſſe, &amp; to reeſtabliſh it in his auncient greatneſſe, dignity, &amp; beautie: We charge &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand al our Liefetenants gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:9"/> &amp; gouernours of our prouinces, baylifes Stewards &amp; their deputies, to cauſe this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Edict to be proclaimed in euery of their gouernments, aſſemblies, &amp; iuriſdictions, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keeping &amp; obſeruing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out impeachme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or ſuffering it to be impeached in any ſort or maner what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be, expreſly forbidding the officers of our courtes of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to impeach it for their part, &amp; putting as wel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as our ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citers &amp; atturneys general &amp; al other perſons vnto ſilence vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight hereof, for ſo is our pleaſure. In witneſſe wherof we haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our ſeals to be put to theſe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Lions</hi> 
                  <date>the .x. day of Sept. the yere of grace 1574. &amp; of our raign y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>Alſo ſigned vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reply, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king being in his counſell, with whom there was alſo the Queene his mother, my Lorde the Duke of <hi>Alanſon</hi> his brother, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> the Cardinals of <hi>Burbo, Lorein,</hi> &amp; <hi>Gwyſes,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince <hi>Dolphin,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dukes of <hi>Gwyſe, Namors,</hi> and <hi>Mayne,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Earle of <hi>Charnie,</hi> the great Eſquire, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords of <hi>Moruillier,</hi> of <hi>Valence,</hi> of <hi>Lanſſak,</hi> of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moges,</hi> of <hi>Foys,</hi> of <hi>Bellieure,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Monluke,</hi> and other Lordes of his priuie counſell then preſent, <hi>Fizes.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <argument>
               <p>And ſealed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> double labels, with the great ſeale in yellow waxe.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="edict">
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:10"/>
            <head>¶ The ſeconde Edict the thirtenth of October.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enry</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,</hi> To al that ſhall ſee this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Edict, gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Though at oure commyng into thys oure realm, &amp; by our letters patte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſigned with our hand the .x. day of September laſt paſt, which was ſent vnto our gouernours, Liefetenants generall in our prouinces, iudges and officers, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhe the fame, and to continue the exacte maintayning and obſeruing thereof, wee haue playnely and particularly ynough de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and opened the inward meaning and intente of our harte, and the deſyre that wee haue to imbrace and receyue all our ſubiects into our good fauour, which wil frame them ſelues to their duetie, and yeld the obedience
<pb facs="tcp:12958:10"/> that God and nature hath bounde them to, being very willing to forget all that is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Yet notwithſtanding bycauſe many of our ſubiects whiche be farre off, and within the townes and places poſſeſſed againſte our authoritie, and peraduenture not well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed and certified of our ſayde meaning, or haue hadde it miſreported vnto them by ſome whiche haue a will to mayntayne ſtill theſe troubles and diſorders for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> particular profite and commoditie whiche they receyue by it, vnder colour that ſince our comming either we haue cauſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Rutters, Swyſers,</hi> and other forces to march in ſome prouinces of our realme, (whiche forces we found ready aſſembled to recouer the ſaide places with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden againſt our ſayde authoritie, and to open the paſſages of our prouinces,) inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnder that pretence to beare men in hande, that our meaning was not to pacifie the affayres of our realme, according to our declaration, although it be the onely thyng whiche we moſt chiefly ſeeke: and we lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe haue bin aduertiſed that ſome of them haue delayed their comming or ſending vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs (to inioy the fauor whiche we haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb facs="tcp:12958:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> them by our ſaid Declaration, for feare of their liues, and for feare to be forced and conſtrained in their conſciences, for that there was not expreſſe mention thereof in our ſayde Declaration, notwithſtanding we haue both hearde, and gently receyued all thoſe which haue come vnto vs for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>And haue graunted perticular paſports, and neceſſarie ſuerties to others, which haue giuen vs knowledge of their deſire to doe the like: For theſe cauſes and other great conſiderations mouing vs therevnto, and to take wholly away al doubt and ſcrupuloſitie from our ſayd ſubiectes, we haue ſufficiently and as much as neceſſitie requireth, ſayd and declared, and by theſe preſentes ſigned with our hande, do ſay and declare, that our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt care and deſire, is to reſtore our ſayde Realme in to the auncient eſtate of quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and tranquillitie, by meanes of ſuche peace as we intende to giue to our ſubiectes, and the clemencie we purpoſe to vſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them, forgetting all that is paſſed, without remembring any part thereof, and intending that none of all our ſubiectes, of
<pb facs="tcp:12958:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> what qualitie, degree, or condition ſo euer they bee, or for what cauſe ſo euer may bee pretended, to haue bene doone and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them during the troubles, or by their occaſion, ſhall any way be diſquieted, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted, or ſyfted by vs or oure officers, eyther in their perſons, goodes, or honours, but that they may lyue in their houſes in all aſſurance, reſt, and tranquilitie, both they, their families, and poſterities. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we folowing (&amp; conforming our ſelues, to our ſayd firſt letters,) mynding moreouer ſo greatly the benefit of peace, that we will not in any wyſe haue them ſyfted, diſtreſſed, nor troubled for their conſciences, but doe vtterly forbid it, and for the ſame wyll make all neceſſarie prouiſion to be put in ready<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>And to the ende that thoſe which are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to come to vs to ſhewe vs their griefes, may doe it ſafely, and ſo likewiſe returne: We will that theſe preſents ſhall ſerue them for ſafeconduct. Prouided alwayes, that as well for theyr comming as theyr going, they take ſafeconductes and Paſportes of the gouernours and Lieftenantes generall
<pb facs="tcp:12958:12"/> of our prouinces by which they paſſe. Whom we commaunde to deliuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without refuſe or delay. Enioyning alſo all gouernours &amp; Captaynes of places, our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticers and officers. Sherifes of Townes and other our ſubiectes, according to theyr dueties, to ſuffer all ſuche trauellers to come and goe ſafely, without giuing or ſuffering to be giuen any moleſtation or impeache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And we promiſe in the faith and word of a king, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our honor, to accompliſh and performe that which is by theſe preſents and ſhall be by vs after accorded and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: And for more greater ſuretie it ſhall be allowed and approued as matter of recorde throughout all the courtes of Parliamentes of our Realm, by the Princes of our bloud, Lordes, Gentlemen, Mayors, Sherifes, and principall dwellers of oure Townes, and others, if neede ſhall require. Thus wee gyue commaundemente to our truſty and welbeloued officers of our Courtes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentes, and our ſayde Liefetenantes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, gouernours, Baylifes, Stewardes, and other deputies, to keepe and obſerue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolably theſe preſentes, without contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:12958:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> or ſuffering any contradiction in what ſort or manner ſoeuer it be: putting our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney generall and all others vnto ſilence: For ſo is our pleaſure. In witneſſe whereof we haue cauſed our ſeale to be put to theſe preſentes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at <hi>Lions</hi> 
                  <date>the thirtienth day of October in the yeare of grace .1574. and of our raigne the firſt:</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>So ſigned, <hi>HENRY:</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>And vpon the reply, By the king, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his councell at <hi>Neufville.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſealed with double labels in yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe waxe.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ A declaration to the moſt Chriſtian king, Henrie the thirde of that name, king of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Yr, the two E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictes that your maieſtie hath cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſince youre newe comming to the Crowne, (which GOD make proſperous vnto you) doe make great ſhewe, that your ſayde Maieſtie is deſirous to ſee a good peace in <hi>France.</hi> And truly, al good people do greatly praiſe God, for the good wil &amp; father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affection, that he hath put into your heart towards your ſayde ſubiects, and deſire that the ſame may there take ſo deepe and liuely roote, as it may vtter it ſelfe more and more in deede and effect. But (according to your ſayd Maieſties complaint in the laſt of thoſe Edictes) many are ſo full of miſtruſt, as they can hardly beleue ſuch affection of peace.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> to be yet throughly imprinted in your heart, the rather for that they ſee your Maieſtie to make warre againſt them, to whom you ſay you intende to giue peace: in ſo muche that, ſeeing on the one ſide a pretence of your will tending to peace, and on the other ſide, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of warre, they knowe not what to determine thereof. Some ſay, they muſt reſt them ſelues rather on the deede, than on the word, paper or ynke. Other ſome thinke that the worde and promiſe of a King, is ground ſufficient to reſte vppon, excuſing youre Maieſties making of warre, with the ſame excuſe that is contayned in your laſt Edict, that is to ſay, that your Maieſtie aſſembled not thoſe forces, but hauing found them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die furniſhed at your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the crown, thought it more requiſite to imploy them, than to ſuffer them to be idle, ſpecially ſeeing that the entertaining of them was ſo charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, &amp; they muſt needs be payd whether they ſerue or no. Some ſay moreouer, that what ſo euer your Maieſtie hath doone touching the execution of war, was but to ſharpen mens apetites vnto peace, which held your townes in their hands, &amp; were in armes againſt you.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> bycauſe feare is a ready meane to make the weaker craue peace of the ſtronger. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſay further, that a noble prince oughte to behaue him ſelfe mildely towardes ſuche as humble them ſelues vnder his obeyſance, and to tame and repreſſe ſuche as make reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt him: and that therefore your Maieſtie hathe iuſt cauſe to make warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe your ſubiects, whiche will not yeeld you their obedience, to whome neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ye would giue peace, if they woulde put off armor &amp; deſire it of you with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe. But (to ſpeake the trueth) all theſe reaſons can not make the greater number, to hazard them ſelues by beleeuing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary (ſay they) to that which they haue ſeene and yet doe ſee with their eyes. And eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe that be in armes, who thinke yee meane to make of them a matter ſeruiceable to your glory and triumph. (as did the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Emperours thoſe barbarous nations whom they ſubdued.) And they grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their beleefe vpon your firſt Edict, by the whyche your ſaid Maieſtie ſeemeth to take for great victorie and matter of triumph, the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table aduentures happened in the warres
<pb facs="tcp:12958:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> paſſed, in the late king your brothers tyme, againſt thoſe that named them ſelues youre ſubiectes, and were in deede Frenchmen borne. Again they grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that a prince ought to repreſſe and tame ſuche as will not obey him, and that God and nature doe teache vs to obey our princes, and ſoueraigne Lordes: but they alſo ſay, that God and nature doe likewiſe teach vs to preſerue our liues, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to the obedience due to princes ought to be ioyned the aſſurance of the ſubiectes lyues, which ſhould not be taken away, but by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of lawe: and that if they were aſſured of that point vppon any other pledges than paper and ynke, there were nothing in the world that they woulde more willingly do, than the yelding vnto you theyr whole obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and ſeruice: and that therefore they are not to bee accompted as traytors and rebels though they ſubmit not themſelues without aſſurance of their liues, bycauſe the former time ſerueth them for a ſufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and leſſon to learne by the harmes of their kinſfolke &amp; friendes, neyther to be light of beleefe, nor to hazard their liues but vpon good warrant. They furder diſcourſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:12958:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> in many other ſortes, your Maieſtie may well conſider, that to ſuch as liue in feare of their liues, all things are holden ſuſpect. For ſome, bycauſe them ſelues are deſirous of peace, are eaſily perſwaded that your maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie deſireth the ſame: and otherſome for the doubt they ſtand in of their liues, are loth to beleeue any thing: and all generally hang in the ballance betweene hope and dread, and knowe not what to truſt vnto, nor whiche way to turne them.</p>
               <p>Now ſir, ſeeing the world in this maner is toſſed, I haue aduentured to take vppon me the humble preſentment of this little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration vnto your maieſtie, thereby to giue you knowledge of three points of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, whiche I intende to verifie by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples notable and worthy of memorie. One is, that neuer Prince founde it good to make warre againſte his ſubiectes, nor to deale rigorouſly and cruelly with them. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother is, that a good peace would not onely make your realme of <hi>France</hi> to floriſhe, and your poore ſubiects to proſper, which are now at the laſt caſt: but alſo make you the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt king that euer was in <hi>France,</hi> yea with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Charlemaine, Clowis,</hi> or any
<pb facs="tcp:12958:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> other. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third point is, that a good peace is not ſo impoſſible to bee made as many iudge it to be. But before I enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe of theſe three points, I wil here recite one hiſtorie much to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe of my former ſaying y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the poore prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded rebels are in ſuch wiſe toſſed betweene hope and dread, as they know not where they are. And God graunt your maieſty a willing deſire, to folow the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of this hiſtorie which I ſhall declare.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Romanes</hi> had in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imes paſt muche war with the <hi>Latines</hi> which were their ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, &amp; (as it were) ſubiect to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by reaſon of their neere neighborhod. But the <hi>Romanes</hi> (hauing ouercome them in many victories) would needes conſtrayne them, to the yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a good part of their goodes and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, by way of an amendes making, for that the <hi>Latins</hi> had broken the treatie of theyr aſſotiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; were becom rebels againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The pore <hi>Latines</hi> being ſore troubled &amp; vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, knew not which way to wind them, for it greeued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> extreamely to indure ſo great a loſſe, ioyned with ſuche ſhame and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; on the other ſide they ſawe no meane left them whereby to maintaine the warres any longer. Herevpon, one <hi>Furius Camillus,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:16"/> a braue and valiant Captaine, and then Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſull of Rome, declared to the ſenate that hee knew a very good &amp; an aſſured meanes, how to make, that the <hi>Latins</hi> ſhoulde neuer after that riſe vp in armes againſt the <hi>Romaines,</hi> but euer liue in peace and fidelitie togyther with them. Then demaunded they of hym what that meanes was. Euen this ſayde he, that nowe when they are vanquiſhed and ſo troubled as they knowe not what to doe, we receyue them for Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> as our ſelues, to enioy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like profites, commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and priuileges as we do: for they looke not for ſo great a benefite at our handes, but prepare them ſelues, both to doe and receyue all hoſtility. And herein is offered vnto vs a very faire occaſion to increaſe oure glory, whiche wee oughte not to let ſlippe, bycauſe there is not a ſurer nor a longer laſting go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, than that which is plauſible vnto the gouerned. But we muſt make haſt, to the intente that nowe while they looke for warre, and prepare for it, we may preuent them with ſo great a benefyte. When <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millus</hi> had ſo put foorth his mind and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the voices ranne, whereof the greater nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:12958:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſtayed vppon his ſayings, and his aduice was followed, for the receyuing of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins</hi> to be Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the enioying of the like rightes and priuileges as the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens did. And from that tyme forwarde they were alwayes ſo firmely vnited to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> as there was neuer any warre or deuiſion betweene them. Now then if your Maieſtie would voutchſafe to imitate thys noble and honorable manner of taking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall peace with the poore pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels (which are your ſubiects) your goodnes, gentleneſſe, and liberalitie ſhewed towards them which deſerue it not, would very gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſe your glory. And ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter would the benefyte be, bycauſe they looke not for it, but are vtterly perſwaded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youre maieſtie wil either haue no peace at al, or elſe ſuch a peace as ſhal only tend to your owne aduantage. And therefore they be fully bent rather to endure all extremitie, than to truſt any more to thoſe fruiteleſſe peaces (whiche they cal <hi>Paix fourrees,</hi> &amp; wherwith (ſay they) they haue alwayes heretofore bin entrapped.</p>
               <p>I wil herevppon recite one other hiſtorie muche to the purpoſe. In the time that the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:17"/> 
                  <hi>Romanes</hi> were at war with the <hi>Samnites,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">i. Liuius b. 9. deca. 1.</note> (a war like people) it happened that <hi>Porthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> and <hi>Veturius</hi> conſuls and captaynes of the <hi>Romane</hi> armie, were by occaſion of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conduct, encloſed in a ſtreight of diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage. And for lacke of a better remedy, they entred into an entreaty of peace with the <hi>Samnites,</hi> which ſo in that ſtraight held their encloſed. The Captain generall of the <hi>Samnites</hi> was a braue yong gentleman na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Pontius,</hi> whoſe father called <hi>Herenni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> had of long time gouerned the ſtate of the <hi>Samnites.</hi> The aduice of this good old man was aſked for the making of peace: he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweared that they muſt ſet goe the <hi>Romans</hi> whom they held already couped vp as Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, without any harme or violence. This aduice was not very well liked of by <hi>Potius</hi> his ſonne, which eftlones aſked him whether he knew no better way than that; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace to paſſe. To whom the good olde man anſweared, that if they miſliked of that his firſte opinion, his nexte aduice was, that they ſhould kill all the <hi>Romanes</hi> which they held then encloſed, without ſuffering of any one of them to eſcape. For (ſaid he) there is betweene both no meane, that may auaile to the winning of a good peace, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame muſt
<pb facs="tcp:12958:17"/> of neceſſitie be gotten either by the vertue of ſome benefite beſtowed vpon the enemie, or elſe by the ſo weakening of them (through the putting of the whole armie to the ſword) as in a long time after they ſhall not be able to recouer again their force. Neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one nor the other of this good mans opinions were followed, but in the ende a diſſimuled peace was made, whiche was not only ſhamefull to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> but alſo by them inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently broken to the vtter ruine &amp; decay of the <hi>Samnites,</hi> whiche vnderſtood in the ende, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the counſell of the good old <hi>Herennius</hi> had bin the beſt to haue bin folowed. Hereof ſir I mean to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, that for aſmuch as the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots</hi> cannot al be encloſed in one ſtrayte, &amp; that if they could, to kil them al (being your ſubiects &amp; not your enemies) it were a thing neither reaſonable nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: ye could not do better, than to agree to ſuche a peace, as might to each parte be both profitable and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, which would cauſe it to be of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. In this reſpect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great warrior <hi>Ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball</hi> demanded peace of the valiant &amp; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>Scipio</hi> after this maner. It is I <hi>Ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nibal</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do demaund the peace, which I would not demaunde if it might not be profitable, and hauing obteyned ſuch a one I wil willingly
<pb facs="tcp:12958:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> keepe it, for the very ſame profit for the which I required it: <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ioniſius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alic. lib. 3.</note> for to bee ſhorte, a good peace ought not to be made in haſt, but rather to be digeſted with meere deliberation, loking to none other end, than the profite of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale. And for this cauſe was it by <hi>Tullus Hoſtilius</hi> king of the <hi>Romanes</hi> ſaide, that <hi>the mutual entercourſe of commodities, was the true band of peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <p>But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming now to intreat of thoſe three points whiche before I proponed, as ſubiect to this declaration. Touching the firſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a prince ought not to take in hand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> making of wars againſt his ſubiects: I ſet down for a true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a people do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer die. The perticulars or ſeueral parts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame do die in deede, but they leaue alwayes behind ſuch as do ſucceede them not only in their inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, but alſo in their quarels &amp; paſſions: ſo as ſeldome or neuer dieth ther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſo very a caytife &amp; vnfortunate wretche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leaueth not another (yea two or three, eyther children, brethren, pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds) which wil be ſorie for his death, &amp; ſeeke reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of it if it wer viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly procured. Wherfore, who ſoeuer hath to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a people, by killing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perticulars profiteth little, bicauſe they leaue
<pb facs="tcp:12958:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> alwais to ſuccede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as are (as it were) maried to their quarels. The ſame is at thys day to be ſene by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpellers (ſo do I tearm them in ſtead of <hi>Hugonots,</hi> and catholikes in ſtead of Papiſts, as did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord of <hi>Valence</hi> in his declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Polonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:</hi> for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe .xv yeres, what by the warres, what by iuſtice, and what by murthers, there hath bene done to death more than 200000. and yet for all that, there are ſtill ſo great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, as it may ſeeme there hath not any one dyed. There is very apparant reaſon why it ſhould be ſo: namely for that a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple dyeth not, bicauſe the perticulars haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes other perticulars to ſuccede them, not onely in their inheritances, but alſo in theyr maners, inſtructions, and other conditions. But contrarywiſe, the great Princes dye, as the late king your brother is deade, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his beſt ſeruitors are deade, your ſelfe alſo are mortall, and your beſt ſeruitors be mortall, wherthrough it is commonly ſeene, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great mens great deuices vaniſh away in the ſmoake, bycauſe that for the moſte parte their ſucceſſours are not of the ſame humor and will, but vſe their gouernment farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, the one vndoing what by the other
<pb facs="tcp:12958:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> was done. In ſo much as it is ſene that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily they pull downe, whome their prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours had ſet vp. Whereof among others, maſter <hi>Enguerran</hi> of <hi>Marigny</hi> may be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which hauing bin in great credite and authoritie, in the time of king <hi>Philip</hi> the faire: was by his brother and ſucceſſor king <hi>Lewes Hutin</hi> ſo abaſed, as he therethrough became a poore man, without any cauſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, other than for the enuie &amp; hate borne to the greatneſſe that he had gotten. Alſo the wiſe Courtiers (which will not their liues, honors, and goods, to depend vpon the life of one onely man) are accuſtomed not onely to pleaſe him that preſently raigneth, but alſo him that is like to ſuccede him. For as <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pei</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Scilla,</hi> there be moe that doe worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne riſing, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne ſetting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the great did in his time many wonderful &amp; incredible things. <note place="margin">Plutarch in Alexandro.</note> For with an armie of .30000. Macedons, he ouercam <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great monarch of al the eaſt leuant in three battels. In the firſt wherof <hi>Darius</hi> had 300000. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was twentie againſt one In the .2. he had .600000. which was .20. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one. And in the third, he had a Miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was thirtie againſt one. He ſubdued
<pb facs="tcp:12958:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> al the Empire of <hi>Darius,</hi> as the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Medes,</hi> the <hi>Parthians,</hi> the <hi>Armenians,</hi> the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians,</hi> with <hi>Egypt, Paleſtine,</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> and generally all the lande habitable of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> and <hi>Aſi,</hi> from <hi>Macedonie</hi> eaſtwarde vnto <hi>India.</hi> But all thoſe faire conqueſtes vaniſhed like ſmoke, and in the ende came to nothing, for he him ſelfe died yong, and left not ſucceſſors of like nobleneſſe and valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie as he was. Whervpon <hi>Titus Liuius</hi> putteth forth this queſtion. <note place="margin">Liuius lib. 9. deca. 1.</note> If <hi>Alexander</hi> the great had taken in hande the warres of his time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Romanes, whether he ſhould as eaſily haue ouercome them as he did <hi>Darius?</hi> he anſwereth no. For though (ſaith he) <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> was a valiant king, and a ſtout &amp; braue warriour: yet was he but one: &amp; in hauing to do with <hi>Darius,</hi> he had to do but with one head. Where, had he had to do with the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, he muſt haue fought with a number of braue Captaines one after another. As <hi>Valerius Coruinus, Martius Rutilius, Caius Sulpicius, Manlius Torquatus, Publius Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, Papirius Curſor, Fabius Maximus, Lucius Volumnius,</hi> the two <hi>Decians, Marcus Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and many other, which would from hand
<pb facs="tcp:12958:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> to hande haue receyued him, ſo as he ſhoulde haue knowne that they vnderſtoode the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the warres. And as concerning Councell, <hi>Alexander</hi> whiche was a yong Prince, could haue no better than they, that were guided by the heades of a whole Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. The concluſion (ſaith <hi>Titus Liuius</hi>) is, That the Macedons had but one <hi>Alexander,</hi> but the Romanes had many captaines which woulde haue matched him, of whome euerie one ſhould haue liued, and dyed without pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill or danger to the ſtate publike: Whereas by the death of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the ſtate of his Monarch was rent and torne in peeces.</p>
               <p>The experience of this diſcourſe of <hi>Titus Liuius,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ti. Liuius lib. 2. deca. 1.</note> was well ſeene in the warres that <hi>Hanniball</hi> had againſt the Romanes. For he was a wiſe and valiaunt Captaine, and knewe as well howe to guide his armie as when to fight. Neyther was he ignorant of the ſtratagemes or policies of warre. And in deede he ouerthrew many of the Romane Captaines, as <hi>Flamminius, Paulus Emilius, Terencius Varro, Marcellus,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But in the ende he was repulſed by <hi>Claudius Nero, Fabius Maximus,</hi> and other,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> and laſt of all ſo vtterly ouerthrowne by the great <hi>Scipio</hi> the <hi>Affricane,</hi> as he founde well that it was no ſmall thing, to haue to doe with a people, which do dayly breede newe Captaines and men of warre. And that wel the perticulars of a people may be vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and ouerthrowne, but the whole people neuer. According to this ſaying of the philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers: <hi>A generall kinde is immortall, by reaſon of the ſucceſsion of perticulars (which ſucceede one another) though euerie perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular in it ſelfe be mortall.</hi> And this reaſon aduiſeth a Prince, not onely to forbeare to ſtriue with his people: but alſo to ſhunne the euill will of them, for feare of after clappes. The Emperour <hi>Caius Caligula,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. cap. 30. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 49. 56. Dion ibid.</note> in his time put to death many of his ſubiects, euen of the chiefeſt, moſt commonly for his owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure without lawfull cauſe, and namely thoſe which founde any faulte with his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and gouernment, thinking by that meanes to haue made away all that hated him, &amp; imagining (though fondly) that with crueltie he might auoyd hatred, wherewith crueltie is ordinarily and worthyly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied. But the moe he cauſed to dye, the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> more his haters encreaſed, and by the kylling of one, he gat the hatred of tenne, in ſo much that perceyuing him ſelfe to be hated of all his people, hee wiſhed that all the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had had but one hed, wherby he ment, that if he had could, he wold haue diſpatched the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al at one ſtroke. But at the laſt experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce taught him, that a people hath many heades (which dayly multiply) where hee had but one, by the taking wherof from him, he was miſerably ſlayne. For although by being Emperour of the worlde, he was of great power: yet was the power of the people founde to be greater than his.</p>
               <p>This was well declared in a Comedie to the great Emperour <hi>Maximine,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Capitolinus in Maximino.</note> great I ſay of ſtature, (for he was in length eyght foote, and in bigneſſe therevnto accordant, but in vertue verie ſmall. This Emperour was of perſonage ſo ſtrong, as with one blowe of his fiſt hee ſtrake out the teeth of an horſe, with one ſpurne of his foote he burſt in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a horſes legge, and with both his handes he pluckt a horſeſhoe in ſunder. With y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural force, he had alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romane Empire at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, ſo as he thought
<pb facs="tcp:12958:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> him ſelfe to be inuincible and immortall. And therefore as one careleſſe of the peoples diſpleaſure, he put to death many gentlemen and other perſons of credite, partly for his pleaſure, and partly for the enuie that he bare vnto their vertues. Therefore as he was one day in the Theatre beholding the playing of a Commedie, one of the players with a good countenance, ſayde aloude as foloweth.
<q>
                     <l>Whom one alone could neuer hurt, a number may confound,</l>
                     <l>The huge and mightie Elyphant, is ſo borne downe to ground:</l>
                     <l>The princely Lion, though he be vnfeareful, ſtrong and ſtout,</l>
                     <l>Is notwithſtanding ouerthrowne, and killed by a rout.</l>
                     <l>The cruell Tygre ſo is left ſtarke deade vpon the ground,</l>
                     <l>For al his fell and furious moode, that paſſeth for no wound.</l>
                     <l>And thou that ſtandeſt in no feare of any one alone,</l>
                     <l>At leaſtwiſe feare the common rage of many knit in one.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maximine</hi> perceyued not that this player had caſt theſe verſes as it were a ſtone into his garden. Or if he did perceiue, yet did he diſſemble it, but within a while after, hee found what ſo was ſayde in ieſt, toward him to turne to good earneſt. For after he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed many cruelties, and therein done to death moe than .4000. Gentlemen without order of iuſtice, he was of all his ſubiectes ſo miſlyked, as (leading an armie againſt the towne of <hi>Aquilee</hi>) the whole countrey con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired
<pb facs="tcp:12958:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> to keepe him from victuals, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any commaundement by him put foorth to the contrarie) by reaſon whereof the ſouldiers (being pinched with famine) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued a hatred againſt him, and began to grudge at him, and ſo at the laſt murthered him. The auncient Romanes woulde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſeeme inuincible againſt ſtrangers, but neuer againſt their owne people. The chiefe of whom were eſteemed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them as the heade, and the meane ſort as the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And if at any time the commons were falne into any mutenie, the heads inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent went about to appeaſe them by gentleneſſe, often thinking good, rather to yeelde them what ſo euer they demaunded, than to aſſay to daunt them by any force of armes. <note place="margin">Ti. Liuius lib. 2. deca. 1.</note> On a time the people, roſe by reaſon of the great rygoure that the bankers and vſurers (to whome they ought money) vſed againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By and by the Conſuls aſſembled their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, to be aduiſed howe that tumult of the people might be appeaſed. After the matter had bene propounded, and ſome ſpeaches paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of it, <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> (a ſeuere man) was of opinion that the bandes of the bankers and
<pb facs="tcp:12958:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> vſurers ought and were to be payd, and that ſuch a libertie was not to be ſet open, as the ſuffering of the people to breake their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes wherevnto they were bounde, but that they ought rather by force to be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to performe them. And that if they wold puniſh ſome of the ringleaders and moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious perſons, that had of that mutenie bin the firſt mouers, al the reſidue would ſhrinke and be ſo diſcouraged, that hardly ſhoulde there any be founde, that would at any time after that, become a captaine to the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or any motioner of ſedition. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary part, the Conſull <hi>Seruilius</hi> was of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that the ſedition was to be appeaſed by gentle meanes, ſaying, that it is much eaſier to bowe a people than to breake them, and that for the conſeruation of the common weale, the gentle meanes is much ſurer than the rigorous, bycauſe if that rigour take not good ſucceſſe, the people become madde, and vtter vnſubduable. By the decree of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the adulce of <hi>Seruilius</hi> was folowed, that they ſhould rather cardeſure, than to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to hazard the eſtate of the publike weale, and for a time the exaction of the handes,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> (wherevpon the bankers and other had lent money vpon intereſt to the people) were ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended. <note place="margin">Ti. Liuius lib. eodem.</note> Within a while after, certaine of the chiefeſt in Rome, cauſed one of the <hi>Tribunes</hi> of the people (whiche was (as it were) the maintayner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liberties of the third eſtate) to be ſlayne as ſecretly as coulde be, bycauſe that vnder the colour of his office, hee had gone about to moue the people to ſedition. The people were ſore grieued at the death of their Tribune: but they ſayd nothing to it, bycauſe they knewe not to whoſe charge to lay it nor whom to blame for it. The noble men (which had cauſed that blowe to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) were verie well a payde, that the people durſt not open their lippes at it, thinking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to haue vſed a verie good mean of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting the ſedition, and that other Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes therby, would take example of it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: They thought ſurely, that by their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the chiefe mouer of the ſedition to be ſlayne, they had taken away the cauſe of ſedition. But in verie deede, they had not the principall efficient cauſe, that is to ſay, the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cour, miſcontentment, and indignation of the people, but they had rather increaſed it
<pb facs="tcp:12958:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> by ſuch vnlawfull execution. What beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thereof? It happened anon after, that there were certain ſouldiers to be leuyed in <hi>Rome</hi> for a peece of ſeruice that the Romanes had in hands, and euerie man thought that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eath of the Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r had then bin falne aſleepe, and for euer forgotten. The Conſuls commaunded one <hi>Vale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> (a man of the third eſtate, that had before<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ene captaine of cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we footmen) to put this compauit in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e anſwered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>atly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would not. Thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Emilius</hi> and <hi>Virginius</hi> then Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> certaine S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s to ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtohi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> towarde. But he eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ping the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Sar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, caſt him ſelf into althroug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the people, and crying out for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſayde, Maiſters let vs ſtande to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to be any were hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tribunes, who dare not ſay any thing, bicauſe they be put to death for doing of their duties. Vpon thoſe wordis of his, notwithſtonding that the Conſols did what they would to appeaſe that ſedition, ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ants, who being wil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ffeted, and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing their m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, did with much adde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>are where
<pb facs="tcp:12958:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Senatours were aſſembled. Then began they to fall to conſultation, howe that vprore might be remedied. Many ſpeaking rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, ſayd, that ſuch boldneſſe and raſhneſſe of the people was to be repreſſed with force &amp; ſeueritie. But the auncient and wiſer Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, which were of opinion that it was not meete for the head to ſubdue the members by violence (but rather by curteſie &amp; gentleneſſe) preuayled in that counſell. For they knewe wel that they had already done too much, in cauſing the Tribune to be ſlaine without or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of iuſtice, (although he had deſerued it) &amp; in offring that extremitie ſo raſhly to <hi>Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> and that in ſuch common miſorders, the my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deſt remedies are the ſureſt and hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurneſt. I will reaccount one example more of this gentle maner of proceding, which for the appeaſing of tumults and ciuil ſeditions, the ancient Romanes liked to vſe, bicauſe it is a point both worthy the marking, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to our purpoſe. It fell out one day in Rome that amongſt the people there was ſo great a mutenie, as the commons woulde needs ſeparat them ſelues from the nobilitie, taking occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therinto, through the grieuous
<pb facs="tcp:12958:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> burthens of their impoſtes, ſubſidies, &amp; other like exactions. And it went ſo far, as the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and meaneſt of the people, did ſeparate them ſelues from the rich and noble, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke their houſes to dwell elſwhere, howbeit without quarelling among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this matter came in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by what meanes the ſayd mutenie might beſt be ſtayed, and the people framed and brought to the yelding of their obedience towardes their ſuperiours and magiſtrates: amongſt the Senatours ran two opinions, one contrarie to the other. The one was of <hi>Appius Claudius,</hi> a man ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeuere and rygorous againſt the common people: whoſe opinion was, that there was no yelding to the common people, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſuch (ſayde he) if it were not brideled, would waxe ſtubborne &amp; proud, &amp; the grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of any thing vnto them vnder colour of this ſedition, would be a maintenance &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of other raſhneſſe and boldneſſe, and an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make them doe the like another time: and therefore they were to be ſubdued by rygour and force. This opinion of <hi>Appius</hi> at the firſt ſight was alowed and followed of the yong Senators, whoſe bloude was
<pb facs="tcp:12958:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> as hote &amp; fierce, as their diſcretions were cold and vnſtayed. The other opinion was of <hi>Menenius Agrippa,</hi> a very good man, curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, of good reputation, and of a right noble houſe, (but poore &amp; a deſpiſer of riches) which ſayde, that the publike affaires were as the body of a man, from the which the good Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion doth not by &amp; by cut off the member that hath an vleer o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> impoſtume, but rather deuiſeth, how he may with good and wiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies heale it, adding alſo, that experience alwayes ſheweth the nature of a people, to become tractable by good and gentle dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and the moſte modeſt and myldeſt, to become fierce with ende and rygorous hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, no more nor leſſe than a wilde beaſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entiſed and flattered becommeth to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>: and the tame being beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; euil intreated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth wilde. And that they ought by bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, &amp; bearing of their plaints and griefes to win their hearts, and by gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and fauourable means to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> backe againe to their obedience. This opinion of <hi>Menenius</hi> was folowed by thoſe auncient wiſe Senatours, that were well practiſed in the gouernment of the common affaires, to
<pb facs="tcp:12958:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> whome alſo ſoone after agreed the yonger ſort, ſomwhat aſhamed to haue holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie opinion to their auncients in yeeres and iudgement. And they excuſed them ſelues of it by the mouth of one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named <hi>Spurius Nautius,</hi> who deſired the auncient to holde their youth excuſed, which is not lightly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſtayed iudgement, aſſuring them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their folowing of the opinion of <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius,</hi> proceded rather of a boyling and vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed affection, &amp; not of purpoſe to ſtand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> termes with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, promiſing from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth to flee the falling into any ſuch fault, and to be conformable to the iudgement of the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as men of more wiſedome and greater experience. The yong Senators were much prayſed, as wel for the reuoking of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as for their ſo curteous excuſing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and ſo <hi>Appius</hi> remayned alone in his rigorous iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts And charge was giuen by the Senate to <hi>Menenius</hi> to make known their good will to the people, which he did in ſuch curteous manner, and with ſo ſweete words, that he not only won their hearts, but alſo abated their furie and fierceneſſe of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. My maiſters (ſaith he) the Senate hath
<pb facs="tcp:12958:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> neyther done you harme, nor meane to doe you any. They are as it were the belly, and you the members of the body: and ſhoulde the members complayne them, that what they labour for is all for the belly? Is it not the belly that nouriſheth, mayntaineth, and keepeth the members, being (as it were) the ſtorehouſe or Garner of all the whole body? When the belly taketh and receyueth ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and nouriſhment, doth it keepe it altogether to it ſelfe? dothe it not rather diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe it through the whole bodie, euen to the fingers of the handes, and to the toes of the feete, which are furtheſt off from it? Do we not ſee that the nouriſhment which it gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, ſerueth not for it ſelfe alone, but for the whole body? And euen in like ſorte doth the Senate employ thoſe things which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde and gather of you. The Tributes and Subſidies that they leuie and receyue, are they not to be employed for the ſeruice of the whole bodie of the common wealth? Ceaſe then my maiſters to complayne you of your ſuperiours and Magiſtrates, which do nothing but for you and for your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations. Whereof doe you complaine
<pb facs="tcp:12958:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> you, and the cauſe of your complaint ſhal be taken away (for a malady cannot better bee cured than by the taking away of the cauſe.) All things ſhal be yeelded you that ſhall bee founde profitable and neceſſary to the whole body of the common weale, which bande of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profit ſhall be one mean of aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to conſerue the one with the other: and the publique othe whiche ſhall be ſworne vnto you, ſhall alſo bee another good guage. By this oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and declaration of this good man <hi>Menenius,</hi> were the people appeaſed, their harts wonne, and them ſelues reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and brought againe vnder the obedience of their ſuperiours and magiſtrates, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, he was greatly commended for hys ſweete manner of ſpeaking, but eſpecially in that hee compared the Senate rather to the belly than to the head, to ſhew that they were rather fathers and nouriſhers than any hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie rulers ouer the people. It is then a thyng very certaine, that the manner of appeaſing the people by gentlenes and profit, (and not by making them warre) is the true mean to bring and hold them vnder obedience as it is alſo for the appeaſing of troubles and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Nero</hi> that was Emperour of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Suetonius in Nerone ca. 38. 40. 42. 47 48. 49. Dion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odem.</note> would needes make warre againſt his ſubiectes, not by preparing an army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, but by cauſing an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them to be ſlayne and murthred one after another, only for his pleaſure ſake. For the whiche alſo he ſet on fire the four corners of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the end to haue burned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole towne, whereof in deede he burned a good part. And when he had done, he made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that he did it to haue buylded it newe agayn, for the doing wherof, he laid ſo great tributes and ſubſedies vpon al the prouinces of the Empire, that hee ſucked the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drie with his fines. Theſe cruelties and oppreſſions, ſo wonne him the euil will of all his ſubiectes, as they one after another reuolted from his obeyſance. And him ſelfe in the end being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned of euery one, (yea euen of thoſe of his owne guard) fled and hid him in a little lodge in the fields where he was diſcouered, and fearing to be taken aliue, killed himſelf. <hi>Galba</hi> ſucceeded him in the Empire. <note place="margin">Suetonius &amp; Dion in Nero. Cor. Tacitus Annalium libr. 13. 14.</note> But ſeing I am entred into the making of ſome diſcourſe concerning the Emperour <hi>Nero,</hi> I will make a little digreſſion which ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:12958:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> not be impertinent nor out of my purpoſe. This Emperour being the laſt of the houſe of <hi>Caeſars,</hi> was as vicious, wicked, and cruell, as the firſt (whiche was <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi>) was vertuous, good, and gentle. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compting of the legend of his wicked lyfe, woulde require too long a time: but it ſhall ſuffice me to tell how he dealt with his beſt ſeruants, and what he gayned by ſuche dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. He had then many noble and good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitours, whiche as long as he truſted them, were to him very louing and faithfull, but when they once ſawe hym to become mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull of their doings, their fidelities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to wauer &amp; diminiſhe, for fearing leaſt he ſhould execute like crueltie vpon them, as he had done vpon many others that had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it. Among other he had ſeuen al right graue and excellente perſonages that were his moſt eſpeciall ſeruantes, and by him em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployde in the greateſt charges of his empire. That is to ſaye <hi>Seneca,</hi> whiche in his youth had bin his tutor and gouernour, and was (as it were) the ſuperintendent of all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of the Empire. <hi>Ruffus</hi> whiche was his Conſtable and great maſter of his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Subrius Flauius</hi> whiche was captayne generall of his guardes. <hi>Sulpicius</hi> after one of his darlings and one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principal Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of the ſame guard. <hi>Corbulo</hi> whyche was his liefetena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the eaſt parts, and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne generall ouer the Romaine army, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Parthes,</hi> who was a valiant war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour and did noble acts againſte <hi>Terida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Vologeſus,</hi> and other kings in the Eaſt, wherethrough he gat greate honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation throughout the worlde. <hi>Vindex</hi> whiche was likewiſe his Liefetenant gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and gouernour in the gouernmente of <hi>Gaul,</hi> a great and mightie prouince, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all that whiche is nowe the realme of <hi>France</hi> with baſe <hi>Alemaigne</hi> on this ſide the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the low cuntrey of <hi>Flanders, Brabant</hi> and <hi>Henalt,</hi> euen vnto the ſea: <hi>Switzerlande, Sauoye, Piedinont</hi> and <hi>Lombardy</hi> euen to <hi>Reniui</hi> where there is a little floud called in olde time <hi>Rubicon,</hi> that ſeparateth <hi>Gaule Ciſalpine</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Italy.</hi> Alſo <hi>Sergius Galba</hi> was his Lieftenaunt generall and gouernour in <hi>Spaine, Portingale</hi> and <hi>Granade,</hi> whiche likewiſe was a very great gouernment that comprehendeth at this daye ſeuen or eyght
<pb facs="tcp:12958:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> realmes. And this <hi>Galba</hi> was a wiſe and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant captaine, but greatly ſtriken in yeares, for hee was .lxxiij. yeeres olde when <hi>Nero</hi> died. Theſe ſeuen great Lordes were good and louing ſeruants to <hi>Nero,</hi> til ſuch time as he becam ſo wicked, &amp; ſo far paſt al goodnes, as he was no longer to be borne withal. His corruption came chiefly by the means of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippine</hi> his mother, which would needs go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne &amp; manage al the affayres of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire (ſo ambitious ſhee was and deſirous to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.) But this was the miſchiefe, that <hi>Seneca</hi> ſuffered himſelfe to be wonne by hir. For ſhe was a faire wel fauoured princes, &amp; with hir entred he into ſo great familiaritie, as he enioyed hir ſecretly. They two then (to the end that al things ſhoulde paſſe through their handes) perſwaded <hi>Nero</hi> (whiche was a yong prince) to take his pleaſures &amp; ſports, and to leaue vnto them the charge and paine of the publique affayres, thinking that the furie of his youth woulde weare away in fond delights and paſtimes, and that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would increaſe with his age, and that in the meane time they ſhoulde better go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne than hee. Of the ſame opinion was
<pb facs="tcp:12958:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Burrus</hi> a ſingular perſon, and next vnto <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> in the waightie cauſes of gouernment. And ſurely about the ſpace of fiue yeeres, they gouerned the Empire reaſonably well. Howbeit; bycauſe <hi>Agrippine</hi> tooke vpon hir to rule all alone after hir owne appetite, theſe two perſons <hi>Seneca</hi> and <hi>Burrus,</hi> toke order out of hand, that the Emperour ſhuld withdrawe ſome parte of the gouernmente fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir, and not ſuffer hir to deale any more with it. But as wiſemen as they were, yet were they greatly deceyued, in that they thought the Emperour <hi>Nero</hi> ſhould in age become wiſe by paſſing his youth in follies: for it happened cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, and he became a moſt wicked and cruell tyrant. And truely it is not to be beleeued, that <hi>Seneca</hi> whyche was ſo ſage &amp; ſo greate a Philoſopher, was ignoraunt that of a diſſolute life in youthe, <hi>Nero</hi> could not gather ought elſe than an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill inclination in age, and that his conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in riot and voluptuouſneſſe (ioyned with a princes libertie) could not otherwiſe do, than drawe him to a maruelous corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But to ſay the truth, <hi>Seneca</hi> was puft vp with ambition and deſire of ſoueraintie,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> notwithſtanding that in his wordes, &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, he deteſted it moſt of all men, for hee was a great hypocrite and deepe diſſimuler, ſpeaking one thing and doing another. Hee preached againſt couetouſneſſe and couetous men, whilſt he himſelfe flattered the olde rich people that had no children, to get thereby their heritages. And he had banks goyng in diuers countries where his ſeruants made gaine of his money through intereſt, ſo as his reuenue came to fyue or ſyxe Millions of ſextercies, which is in value eyght hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſand poundes of rent. He preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt pomps and delights, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane while had the faireſt houſes, and beſt builded that might be, not farre inferiour to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud palaces and royall houſes of <hi>Nero</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and therevnto the moſt fayre delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gardins that were poſſible to be ſeene, togither with ſo ſumptuous moueables that he had .50. tables of Cedar with their treſtles and frames of yuorie, and ſo muche ſyluer veſſell and tapiſtry as furniſhed euery houſe that he had throughly. He inueyed agaynſt whoredome, when he enterteyned the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and delighted in the company of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſſes.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> He cried out and ſtormed agaynſte flattery, and ther was not a finer nor craftier courtier in that qualitie than he, for he could make the court to euery body, (yea euen to the Pages and varlets of the chamber) from whome any commoditie was to be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And laſtly he exclaymed againſt ambition, and in the meane while woulde needes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne all himſelfe, &amp; ſuffer nothing to paſſe but through his hands. Moreouer, to heare him ſpeake, was nothing elſe but hony, but eloquence, but holyneſſe, but wiſedome and knowledge. And to be ſhort, if he were now liuing, he woulde deſerue to bee the greateſt Cardinall of all <hi>Fraunce.</hi> But now to come again to our matter. <hi>Seneca</hi> hauing let loſe the reynes to the Emperour <hi>Nero,</hi> and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering him ſo farre foorth till he had done a thouſande miſchiefes and cruelties agaynſte one and other, great and ſmall (as his fanſie led him) began to doubt leaſt the like might happen vnto himſelfe. Alſo <hi>Burrus, Ruffus, Sulpitius</hi> and <hi>Flauius,</hi> and diuers other great Lordes that folowed the court by reaſon of their eſtates and offices, entred into the like feare and miſtruſt, eſpecially after they had
<pb facs="tcp:12958:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeene him do to death his mother <hi>Agrippine</hi> vppon diſpleaſure only, that ſhe woulde ſtill take vpon hir the dealing with the matters of the Empire. They then to auoyde hys crueltie, made a conſpiracie to kill him, but the enterpriſe was diſcouered in ſuch ſorte, as contrariwiſe, he cauſed all them to be killed. Neuertheleſſe before they were executed, he woulde needes talke with <hi>Sulpicius</hi> one of the Captaynes of his guarde, and with <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> the generall of the ſame. Of <hi>Sulpicius</hi> he demaunded wherefore hee had broken hys othe in conſpiring agaynſte him. For that (anſwered he) there was no other meane to heale thee of thy naughtineſſe. He lykewiſe did aſke of <hi>Flauius,</hi> wherfore he had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt him: I haue (ſayd he) loued, and hated thee about any man in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thee, ſo long as there remained any hope that thou wouldeſt become a good Prince: and hated thee, when I ſawe there was no more hope of thee but that thou wouldeſt growe euery daye worſe and worſe: For ſo long as thou deſeruedſt to bee beloued, thou hadſt not a more faythfull and louing ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant than I: but when I ſawe thee once to
<pb facs="tcp:12958:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> become a manqueller, a murtherer, a player of enterludes, a fencer, and a touneburner, I could not but hate thee extremely. Thoſe braue anſwers of thoſe two captiues or cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne priſoners, made <hi>Nero</hi> more afrayd tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other thing, as one maruelouſly aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to heare that they durſt ſpeake vnto him ſo boldly. In the ende, after he had put them to death, and all other that were but neuer ſo little ſuſpected of that conſpiracie, hee made great ſacrifices of thankeſgiuing vnto <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> his deliuerer, as one that thoughte hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe nowe to haue gotten the vpperhand of all his enimies, and in place of amendment, he gaue him ſelfe to doe worſe than before, aſſuring hym ſelfe to raigne then fortie yeeres and more through the prophecyings of his Magiciens and deuines which had wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to take heede to the yeare of his age 73. and he had then ſkarſely accompliſhed 29. But as he continued his naughtie diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered courſe, beholde <hi>Vindex</hi> became a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolter from his obeyſance, togither with all the prouinces and countries vnder his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernemente, whereof though the loſſe were not ſmall, yet was not <hi>Nero</hi> therwith much
<pb facs="tcp:12958:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> troubled. But when he vnderſtoode that the olde Captayne <hi>Galba</hi> hys gouernour of <hi>Spayne</hi> was reuolted, he was greatly aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, fearing leaſt that which the magiciens had ſayde vnto him, touching the age of .73. was to bee vnderſtanded, not of hys owne yeeres, but of <hi>Galbas,</hi> whiche was then of the ſame age. <hi>Corbulo</hi> which was then with a great armie in the Eaſt, was greatly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to do as <hi>Vindex</hi> and <hi>Galba</hi> had done. But he as one that would neuer thereto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, continued alwayes ſo faithfull &amp; truſtie to <hi>Nero,</hi> as he gate therfore euill will, &amp; was blamed of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ſaid he was a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of tyrannie. Yet for all this, <hi>Nero</hi> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leaſt he ſhould doe as his other felowes did, ſent for him by louing letters to come &amp; ſpeake with him. <hi>Corbulo</hi> making no doubt of the matter, tooke the iourney in hand: but before he was come to the place where <hi>Nero</hi> was, he was at <hi>Cenchre</hi> betrayed &amp; taken by the aſſailaunts whiche <hi>Nero</hi> before had ſente thither to kil him, who ſeing how the world went, &amp; weying his fault in the not doing as other did, drewe out his dagger, &amp; therwith ſtrake himſelf to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vttering theſe for
<pb facs="tcp:12958:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> his laſt wordes <hi>I am worthy.</hi> Nowe ſir by this ſhort digreſſion it may be gathered, that the beſt meane to make a Prince to be well and faythfully ſerued of his ſeruauntes and officers, is to be a good and faythfull Prince towards them, withoute miſtruſting of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to vſe clemencie and gentlenes (and not rigour &amp; crueltie) in his gouernment. For a good maſter maketh a good ſeruant. And yee haue not ſo good a ſeruaunt, but hee will bee diſcouraged when he ſeeth his maiſter to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt him, or his ſeruice not to pleaſe hys maſter, ſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the caſe concerneth the ſeruice of a prince, who hath power of lyfe &amp; death, ouer his ſubiects and ſeruants. For let the ſeruant of a prince receyue a ſowre coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his maieſtie, and by and by he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into the feare of the loſſe of his life, or at the leaſt of his goodes and eſtimation. But before I paſſe out of this matter of <hi>Nero,</hi> I wil on the contrary part ſet downe an example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gentle and curteous Prince <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> (of whome your maieſtie hath heretofore borne the name.) And that is, to ſhewe that thoſe two Emperous haue both of them fayled the loſſe of theyr lyues
<pb facs="tcp:12958:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> by following of two extremities. For <hi>Nero</hi> hauing a will to gouerne all vpon hys owne head, was caſt headlong into the miſlikyng and hatred of his people, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of his life. And <hi>Alexander</hi> by ſuffering him ſelfe to bee ruled by the fantaſies of other men, wonne the euill will of his nobilitie and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of war, which vnhappily ſlew him. And of a trueth, a man muſte alwayes keepe an euen hande, and eſchewe extremities in all things, and ſpecially in matters of ſtate and gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For as <hi>Horace</hi> ſayth.<note place="margin">Horace lib. 1. Sermo. Satira. 2.</note>
                  <q>
                     <l>Oft whilſt the foole doth one fault flie,</l>
                     <l>He falles into the contrarie.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nero</hi> (as I ſaide) had good and wiſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants about him to his officers. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had ſuffered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beare authoritie awhile, hee fell into miſliking of them, and therevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would not be ruled any more by them. <note place="margin">Lampridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andro. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodianus lib. 6.</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe <hi>Alexander</hi> woulde doe nothing at all, but by the councel of wiſe men, of whom he had a great number about him and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſurely he did well. Neuertheleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of hiſtories find fault with him in this, that he gaue too muche authoritie to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mámea,</hi> which otherwiſe had bin a good
<pb facs="tcp:12958:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> woman, but that ſhee was not only greedy in gathering of goods from the poore people, but alſo a couetous niggarde towards ſuch as ſerued the Emperour hir ſonne beſide the which ſhe was very ambitious, aſpiring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to the gouernement of the affayres, euer ſorie to ſee hir ſonne ſo curteous &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in his gouernemente: for where hee was ſurnamed <hi>Seuerus,</hi> hee tooke that aſwell of his predeceſſor <hi>Septimius Seuerus,</hi> as of his ſeuere obſeruing of warlike diſcipline: but otherwiſe he was the moſt affableſt and ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleſt prince in the world. Neuertheleſſe, by his yeelding ſo much authoritie to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mámea,</hi> he ſo gate the euill will of hys gentlemen and men of warre, as by way of a conſpiracie they ſlew them both togyther. Truely it was a ſpectacle very piteous, to ſee this gentle yong Prince (when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratours entred the chamber to kill him) runne and caſt him ſelfe betweene the armes of his mother, lamentably crying, <hi>Ah mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mother, you are heereof the cauſe.</hi> So were they wretchedly flayne, the one in the others armes, to the greate damage of the Empire, for the loſſe of ſo good and gentle
<pb facs="tcp:12958:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> a prince, who in al other things gouerned him ſelfe aſwell as might be poſſible, through the good and wiſe aduiſes of ſuch excellent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, as were of his priuie counſell: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whome the chiefe was doctor <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian,</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſingularly learned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ciuil law, and very well practiſed in matters of the ſtate, and iſſued of the houſe and ſtocke of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> whome hee ſerued as his chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celer.</p>
               <p>This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not an old doterd of a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge nation, ignorant of the lawes, manners, and cuſtomes of the countrie, drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> ſhop to deale with ſealing: he was one made of another manner of metall. But in ſumme (as I ſayd) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fault of this good Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Alexander</hi> in giuing his mother too much authoritie, coſt both him and hir theyr liues. And truely that fault of his was not ſmall. For <hi>Alexander</hi> ought to haue conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what hee had learned of <hi>Heliogaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> his coſin and predeceſſor, <note place="margin">Lampri. in Heliogaba. Dion in pſeudo Antonino.</note> which <hi>Helioga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balus</hi> gouerning by his mother <hi>Semiamira</hi> (without whoſe aduiſe nothing paſſed tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the common wealth) was incontine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye deſpiſed of all the worlde, and after
<pb facs="tcp:12958:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> he had raigned not paſſing three yeeres, was by certaine rebels ſlayne very yong, and had his body togither with his ſayde mothers, drawen through the fylth of the riuer <hi>Tiber.</hi> And therevpon it was decreed by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, that neuer woman ſhould enter into the counſel. <note place="margin">Froyſſart lib. 1. cap. 4 15. 24.</note> The gentle King <hi>Edward</hi> of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land the thirde of that name, gouerned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe farre otherwiſe. He was ſonne to <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſeconde a cruell king, that was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of his kingdome by his ſubiects, and to the Lady <hi>Iſabell</hi> daughter of <hi>Philip</hi> the fayre, king of <hi>France.</hi> This Lady <hi>Iſabell</hi> Queene of England, was the cauſe that hir ſonne was crowned King, by the eſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of the Realme, and therefore thought he ſhould doe nothing but by hir councell, as in very deede he dyd not for a tyme, but gaue to hir the chiefe authoritie touching the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his realme. But it happened that this good Queene mother to reuenge hir ſelfe of certayne of the nobilitie at hir plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, cauſed hir ſonne to committe certaine cruelties, for the whyche hee was miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and muche blamed of his ſubiectes. Whiche when thys gentle King <hi>Edwarde</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> perceiued, iudging it beſt rather to looſe the fauour of his mother than of his people, he neyther woulde fall into like perill as did <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Alexander Seuerus,</hi> nor yet put his mother to death as <hi>Nero</hi> did: but made hir to be beſtowed in a ſtrong, howebeit a very faire and pleaſant caſtell, of large circuite, wherein there were many goodly courtes, gardens, and walkes, incloſed with walles: and appoynted hir a good companie of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and gentlewomen, with men of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and honour, to ſerue hir after hir ſtate. And bycauſe ſhe was of the houſe of <hi>France,</hi> and Queene mother of Englande, he aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hir a ſufficient reuenue for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of hir eſtate. And to honour hir as his mother, hee went to viſite hir twice or thrice a yeere. But neyther woulde he euer ſuffer hir to paſſe out of the precinct of the caſtell, nor to meddle any more with the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the realme. And he was muche eſteemed, as well of ſtrangers as of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, for his valiant and manly heart, in that he would not ſubmit himſelfe vnder the rule of a woman. But let vs returne againe to our former matter, touching ſuch Princes as
<pb facs="tcp:12958:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> haue vndone them ſelues by making warre againſt their ſubiectes. <note place="margin">Titus li. 17. Sueton in Vitel. 10. cap. 10.</note> The Emperour <hi>Vitellius</hi> ouerthrewe and made a great ſlaughter of the Romanes, in his battell had againſt <hi>Otho:</hi> his ſouldiers ſeeing ſo many deade bodyes in the fielde, were therefore verie ſorowfull, but eſpecially for that there was of them few or none that founde not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe deade bodies ſome of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents &amp; friends (for they were all Romanes) whoſe death miniſtred to them muche cauſe of griefe, vpon the which occaſion they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally deteſted thoſe ciuill warres had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Vitellius</hi> and <hi>Otho.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vitellius</hi> one day walking through the field wher the dead bodies of that ouerthrow lay, and ſeeing ſome ſtop their noſes, did as it were in mockage thereof, and as one glad of the ſlaughter, vtter this deteſtable ſaying: <hi>the body of a ſlaine enimie hath a good ſent, but the body of a ſlain citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath yet a better</hi> But not long after, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyrant which found ſo muche ſweetneſſe in the ſauour of his ſlaine citizens, was him ſelfe ſlaine as ſhamefully as he poſſibly might be. For being taken and bound by ſuche as conſpired againſt him: he
<pb facs="tcp:12958:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> was brought into the market place with a halter about his necke, all naked from the waſte vpward, his apparell all to torne, and his handes faſtned behinde him, his chin alſo being vnderſet with a bodkin, to make him hold vp his head. With which furniture hee was in deriſion harryed through the ſtreetes, not without dirt and filth flung in his face, till he came to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gibet, where he was ſlaine and cut in peeces, &amp; laſtly caſt into <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> That was the rewarde that he reaped of his pleaſure taken in the ſmel of the dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of his citizens. <note place="margin">Trebellius Pollio in Gallieno &amp; in Ingenio tyranno.</note> The Emperour <hi>Gallien</hi> made war againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitants of <hi>Bizance</hi> his ſubiectes. <hi>Bizance</hi> was then a goodly flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing citie, which was after named <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great. This <hi>Gallien</hi> hauing gotten the poſſeſſion of this goodly citie, the townſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof had yelded themſelues to his deuotion, cauſed to be ſlain &amp; murthred, (contrary to his word) al the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantes of the ſame (yong and olde) without mercie, none other eſcaping, than ſuch as he coulde not come by. And he vſed like crueltie againſt many other good towns wherin his maner was to leaue no male vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killed, ſo beſtly a bludſucker he was. Alſo this
<pb facs="tcp:12958:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> other good qualitie he had, that <hi>Sardanapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> was neuer plunged more deepely in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate lecherie and voluptuouſneſſe than he. Theſe two faire properties of crueltie and lecherie, cauſed the moſt part of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of the Empire to reuolt from his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. In ſo much, that in dyuers coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries there roſe vp againſt him eyght and twentie captaines, whereof one got one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, another got another, ſo as a great part of the nations ſubiecte to the Empire of Rome, did cut them ſelues quite off from their obedience to the Empire, which coulde neuer after that recouer againe his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but being extremely hated, was ſlayne by a captaine of <hi>Sclauonie.</hi> And when one came to him and ſayd, ſyr, Fraunce is reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt you. Well well (ſayd he) ſhal we leaue our good chetre for thoſe pyde coates? (for the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chmen then ware their garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts embrodered with coloures.) And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſayde vnto him, that Egypt was reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from his obeyſance: Wel wel (quoth he) cannot we forbeare the ſurplices of Egypt. The like wordes vſed he of other Prouinces, when tydings was brought him of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolting.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> Wherevpon by the way I note, howe welnere ordinarily it happeneth, that when one Prouince or towne reuolteth, the reuoltes of other doe eaſily folowe, bycauſe naturally men deſire change, and are neuer contented with their preſent ſtate, but hope ſtill vpon better, when it turneth commonly into worſe. The example of which manner of reuoltment, is well to be ſeene in this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of <hi>Gallien,</hi> for after Fraunce was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolted, the other Prouinces enſued one after another. It was alſo to be ſeene in that I ſayde before of <hi>Nero,</hi> from whome as firſte Fraunce and then Spaine reuolted, ſo the other Prouinces folowed. <note place="margin">Ti. Liuius lib. 3. dec. 3.</note> When <hi>Hanniball</hi> had wonne the iourney of <hi>Cannas</hi> againſt the Romanes, a great part of their ſubiectes one after another forſooke them, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yeelded them ſelues to <hi>Hanniball.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ti. Liuius lib. 7. de. 1.</note> The like may be learned of the warres which the Romanes had againſte their confederates, <note place="margin">Appianus de bello Social.</note> which reuolted one after another, yea and banded them ſelues together againſt them. <note place="margin">De bello Gal. lib. 7. cap. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> doth alſo write, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after he had brought vnder his obeyſance the townes of Fraunce: they of <hi>Autun,</hi> which were the firſt that drew
<pb facs="tcp:12958:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> him into Fraunce, were alſo the firſte that withdrewe them ſelues from him, and made the moſt part of the other townes to doe the like, in ſuch ſort, as he founde more painefull his gouerning therin at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he did his conquering of them at the firſt. Wherevpon hee ſaide, that the french men are naturally enclyned to reuolting, when the way is once opened to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I could alledge an infinit nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other examples to this purpoſe, but the matter is cleare inough of it ſelfe, &amp; requireth no large diſcourſe, and therefore I wil now returne to my purpoſe. <note place="margin">Froiſ. lib. 2. cap. 95. 96. 97. 98.</note> 
                  <hi>Lewes</hi> the laſt Earle of Flaunders (for after him the Earldome fell into the houſe of <hi>Burgoign,</hi> and from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into the houſe of <hi>Auſtrich,</hi> wher it now tarieth,) made great and grieuous warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſubiectes of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> bycauſe they were not to him ſo obedient as he woulde them (as people that in deede were alwayes too ſtubborne againſt their Prince.) He ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing then continued a long and ſharpe ſiege, by cutting off their victuals, brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them a maruellous famine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through they were driuen into an vtter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire. The poore people deſired the Dutches
<pb facs="tcp:12958:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> of <hi>Brabant,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Liege,</hi> and certaine other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobilitie, to entreate for ſome good peace, with the ſaid Earle their Lorde. The which the ſayde Lords tooke great paynes to do, but the Earle would in no wiſe agree to any other ende, than that all the inhabitantes of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> ſhould in a certain place come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him barefoote and bare headed, with hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters about their neckes, demaunding pardon for their rebellion, and their pardonings ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe to ſtande vpon his pleaſure. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore <hi>Gauntois</hi> vnderſtoode no better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to be hoped for tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, they deſperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined (rather than ſo) to hazard them ſelues to dy with their ſwords in their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. Whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the town there iſſued about 5000. <hi>Gauntois</hi> (compelled therto by famin, as the wolfe is to the wood) which ſped them towards <hi>Bridges,</hi> where the Earle their lord then lay with his power. And when they came ſomewhat neare the ſayde towne of <hi>Bridges,</hi> their captaines, and certain Fryers that were with them, beganne to encourage them, &amp; tolde them that their caſe was like to the children of Iſraell, which had humbled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues as much as might be vnto <hi>Pharao,</hi> and yet he had neuer the more pitie vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> And that euen as God had drowned <hi>Pharao</hi> in the depth of the ſea for his rygour reached out to the Iſraelites: ſo woulde he puniſhe <hi>Lewes</hi> their Lorde for his crueltie extended to the <hi>Gauntois.</hi> Whileſt the Fryers were thus preaching to the poore hungerſtarued people, beholde, the armie of the Earle (which were fourtie thouſande men in good aray,) came raunging towardes the ſayde fiue thouſande famiſhed <hi>Gauntois,</hi> who (on the one ſide being paſt all hope of any fauor at their Lordes hande, and on the other ſide, readie to be ſwalowed vp by famine) deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined verily to vanquiſhe or to dye, and therevpon fought ſo valyantly and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, as they ouerthrewe the Earles armie, ſacked his houſes, and tooke his towne of <hi>Brudges,</hi> and gate vnder their gouernment all his townes of <hi>Flaunders, Audenarde</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted. The Earle ſaued him ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Brudges,</hi> after the ouerthrowe of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. And when <hi>Brudges</hi> was taken, he hid himſelf in the houſe of a poore woman, which beſtowed him in a garret vnder a little couch, vpon the which hir yong children were layde to ſleepe. The next morning he founde the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> meanes to ſteale out of the towne ſecretly, diſguiſed in a Coſterdmongers apparell, wherwith he gat into <hi>Liſle,</hi> where he taryed in ſafetie. But after that time neuer ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued peaceably in his countrey, for whereas before he had but only the <hi>Gauntois</hi> agaynſt him, (whiche hee might eaſily by gentle meanes, haue brought vnder his obeyſante:) he was after that banded agaynſt by all the whole countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roboam</hi> Kyng of Iſraell, <note place="margin">3. Re. cap.. 12.</note> a Prince euill aduiſed (althoughe he were the ſonne of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> a wiſe father.) Woulde needes put vpon his people greater tributes and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies, than euer his ſayde father dyd. The people opening to him their griefes, by way of complayntes, ſhewed them ſelues vnable to ſuſtayne ſo great charges. Wherevpon <hi>Roboam</hi> brought the matter to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, to the ende they myght determine what beſt therein was to be done. The olde and ſage Counſellours were of opinion, that his beſt was to graunt to his ſubiectes their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, in not augmenting of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtes, wherethrough he might at his newe comming to the Crowne, winne the hearts
<pb facs="tcp:12958:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> of his people, to the rendring of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and franke good wil to hys ſeruice. The counſellours whiche were yong (as well in iudgement as in yeeres, and ſuche as at this day there are too many of,) were of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying, that it was not mete for a kyng to graunt the people their willes, by doing whereof (ſayde they) he ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue lawe of them to whome he ought to gyue lawe, and ſubiecte him ſelfe to them that ought to be ſubiecte to him: but rather, that he ought to make them knowe hym for their Prince and ſoueraigne Lorde, whoſe office was to commaunde, and theirs abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to obey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roboam</hi> folowing this opinion, woulde needs lay great taxes and impoſitions on his people, by reaſon whereof the moſt part of them (that is to ſay) tenne partes of twelue, rebelled againſt him, and rayſed for their Kyng one <hi>Ieroboam.</hi> Wherevpon the ſayd <hi>Roboam</hi> prepared an armie of 80000. men, for the repreſſing of thoſe rebelles, wherein he loſt both his labour and time, for <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> continued King in peace. And from that time forth, that kingdome remained deuided
<pb facs="tcp:12958:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> in two: <note place="margin">Philip de Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnies lib. 1. cap. 3.</note> King <hi>Lewes</hi> the eleuenth (as fine &amp; ſubtil a prince as euer was in Fraunce) at his comming to the crowne gouerned him ſelfe very yll, in diſplacing and hindering of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good and ancient ſeruitours, that had don great ſeruice to <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeuenth his father, in the recouering of his realme, the moſt part whereof, the Engliſhmen long time enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Wherewith the nobles being diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, rayſed againſt their ſayde king a ciuill warre, which they called the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth. To them many townes and commonalties alſo adioyned them ſelues, by reaſon of the great impoſtes that the king put vpon them. But the wiſe king (knowing his faulte) ſought all the meanes poſſible for the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of that warre, therein folowing the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and councell of his good friend <hi>Fraunces Sforze</hi> the Duke of <hi>Millaine,</hi> which councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obtaining of peace, to deny no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their demaundes. And in deede by graunting their requeſts, he appeaſed thoſe ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil warres, and was al his life after ſerued of thoſe noblemen &amp; gentlemen, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were againſt him in the ſame, towards whom he neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſo much as any deſire of reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gement.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> It may be ſayd, that what the king did here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, was done vpon policie. But howe ſo euer it was done, the Frenchmen till theſe dayes were neuer ſo Italionated, as to beare malice long in their heartes. And this wiſe king woulde neuer hazarde his common wealth, by giuing of battell vnto his people, ſaying, that he would not commit his eſtate (which was ſo good and ſo great, as the king of a royall Realme) to the perill of ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine a thing as a battell. And after the peace made, hee frankely confeſſed, that hee ſawe him ſelfe in great perill of looſing his kingdome, and had determined in his mynd, to haue ſaued him ſelfe at <hi>Millaine,</hi> or elſe amongſt the <hi>Switzers,</hi> if <hi>Paris</hi> had not helde with him, but bene wonne and poſſeſſed by his aduerſaries. <note place="margin">Froiſſart lib.</note> 
                  <hi>Edwarde</hi> the ſeconde of that name King of Englande, for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>Hugh Spencer</hi> his chiefe mynion, made warre againſt his ſubiectes, and put to death many of his Princes and nobles with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anye order of iuſtice, in ſo muche as Queene <hi>Iſabell</hi> his wife, with his ſonne and hirs (to ſhunne his furie and crueltie) were fayne to flee into Fraunce, who after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned
<pb facs="tcp:12958:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> agayne into Englande with hyr ſayde ſonne, and a ſmall force, which ſhe had gotten by the meanes of a meane Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man called ſyr <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Henawd,</hi> brother to the Earle of <hi>Henawd.</hi> And being aryued in Englande, founde all the people readie at hir commaundement, as thoſe that had taken a great diſpleaſure agaynſt the King, by reaſon of his crueltie: So as ſhe beſieged hir ſayde huſbande, tooke him pryſoner, and beſtowed him in the Tower of London. Then cauſed ſhe all the eſtates of the realme to be aſſembled, by whome Kyng Edward the ſeconde (for his crueltie committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt his nobilitie) was founde and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced vnworthy to be Kyng any longer, and ſo was depriued of his dignitie. And whyle he was yet aliue, and pryſoner in the ſayde Tower of London, the ſayde eſtates crowned his ſonne Edwarde the thyrde their Kyng, of whome I haue ſpoken afore, and ſhewed that he did the like to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <note place="margin">Dioniſ. Hal. 4. &amp;. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Tarquine</hi> the proud a King of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, was by his people driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well for his gouerning ouer proudly, as for ſuffering his ſonne to violate a woman
<pb facs="tcp:12958:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> of honour named <hi>Lucrecia,</hi> and being thence baniſhed, he ſent his embaſſadours thither for the procuring of his peace, and reſtabliſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his eſtate: many gaue their conſents to reſtore him, and had he proceeded in gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and tractable maner, there had bene great likelyhoode of the recouerie of his kingdome. But being vnable to maiſter his own pride, he gathered together as many as he coulde get to take his part, and with <hi>Porſena</hi> kyng of the <hi>Hetrurians</hi> (whome he rayſed vp to ayde him) made warre againſte the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes. This war procured him ſuch hatred of the Romanes which hadde bene his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, as they would neuer after returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his obeyſance: in ſo much as both he and all his poſteritie were depriued from off the kingdome, and the eſtate of that Monarchie changed into a publike ſtate. And from that time forth the name of King was deadly hated and abhorred among the Romanes. And no maruell though the name of King were ſo ſore hated of the Romanes for one mans faulte, that euen when the ſame ſtate returned againe to a Monarchie vnder <hi>Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Caeſar,</hi> neither he nor his ſucceſſours wold
<pb facs="tcp:12958:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> be called kings, but Emperours. For it hath happened ſo to dyuers other names. The name of Tyrant, which at this day ſoundeth ſo yll, and is of euerie man hated, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our Elders an honourable name, &amp; ſignified none other thing but lord, inſomuch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Virgil</hi> whoſe onely drift in his <hi>Aeneiad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Virgil Eneid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lib. 7.</note> was to aduaunce the godlyneſſe &amp; vertue of his <hi>Aeneas,</hi> calleth him Tyrant. Likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of <hi>Iudas</hi> (which ſignifieth a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour,) was in times paſt reputed honourable, and yet by reaſon of one mans faulte, it is nowe taken for a traytour. And before the Emperour <hi>Neroes</hi> time, this name <hi>Neron</hi> (which in the olde Sabin tong ſignifieth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) was eſteemed as a glorious name, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after the days of <hi>Claudius Nero,</hi> which ouercame <hi>Aſdrubal Hannibals</hi> brother, &amp; his 50000. men: but for the offences of one only man, the ſame is now taken for a tyrant. So much may the wickedneſſe of one man do, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter defacing of a faire &amp; honorable name for euer. God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the vices of ſome of vs frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do not beſpot y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which hath heretofore bin eſteemed and honored throughout al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: which thing I am ſore afeard of, if we mend not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoner:
<pb facs="tcp:12958:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> for alreadie in Germanie, they cal al french<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men indifferently <hi>Schelmes.</hi> Continuing our examples, I will recite you one which is the more to be noted, for that it was done by the way of iuſtice.</p>
               <p>After the death of the great <hi>Herode</hi> king of <hi>Iudea, Samaria, Galile,</hi> and <hi>Idumea,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">As Ioſephus De bello Iud. lib. 18. cap. 1. 2. 3.</note> there aroſe a ſtrife and contention betweene <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelaus</hi> and <hi>Herodes Antipas</hi> his ſonnes. <hi>Archelaus</hi> would needs make wars againſt his ſubiectes, vpon a verie ſlyght occaſion, in ſuche wiſe, as for the giuing of one blowe, he cauſed three thouſand perſons to be ſlaine by his horſemen, whome he made to trauerſe and runne through the whole aſſembly of his people. Wherevpon his brother <hi>Antipas</hi> ſped him ſtrayght vnto Rome, where before <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> he accuſed <hi>Archelaus,</hi> for at that time welneere all the Kings of the world were ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. The Iewes alſo ſente from <hi>Iudea</hi> to Rome, fiftie Ambaſſadours, to accuſe hym before <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and to ſhewe how vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy he was to raigne, that had vpon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple committed ſuche crueltie: and that alſo there was no better curteſie to be loked for
<pb facs="tcp:12958:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> at his handes, that woulde ſo ſoone after the death of his father (and immediatly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys entrie) commit actes ſo cruell and vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. In conſideration wherof they beſought <hi>Auguſtus</hi> to gyue them rather <hi>Antipas</hi> for their King. <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> tooke knowlege of this matter, neuertheleſſe, for that hee bare ſome fauour and friendſhip to <hi>Archelaus:</hi> be confirmed his ſucceſſion in <hi>Iudea, Samaria,</hi> &amp; <hi>Idumea,</hi> and aſſigned <hi>Galile</hi> to <hi>Antipas.</hi> But therewith hee exhorted <hi>Archelaus</hi> to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning of him ſelfe thencefoorth more mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and gently towards his ſubiects. <hi>Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> returning into his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey with ſo good ſpeede at <hi>Auguſtus</hi> hande, behaued him ſelfe there, more cruelly than before. Wherevpon hee was agayne accuſed at <hi>Rome,</hi> and there condemned by the Senate, to whome <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> had referred the examination of the matter, in ſomuche that all his goodes were confiſcate to the Emperour by ſentence of the Senate, and hee him ſelfe was baniſhed to <hi>Vienna</hi> in <hi>Dauphine,</hi> there to ende hys dayes, as he miſerably did. After this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Iudea, Samaria</hi> and <hi>Idumea,</hi> were ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſuche gouernours as the Emperour
<pb facs="tcp:12958:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> did eſtabliſhe, as by <hi>Coponius</hi> and <hi>Annius Rufus</hi> in the raigne of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> and by <hi>Valerius Gratus,</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> (that cruell man, whiche iudged our Sauiour to death) during the dayes of <hi>Tiberius.</hi> The concluſion is, that <hi>Archelaus</hi> for his warring and ouerrigorous dealing with hys ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, miſerably ended his dayes, and was the cauſer of the alteration of the ſtate of hys countrie. Vpon this matter of alteration of ſtates, I ſay by the way, that it hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten fallen out, and ſtill dothe, that when Monarchies haue bin exceſſiuely corrupted with vice, they haue bin changed into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weales: and likewiſe when the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weales haue once bin corrupted, they alſo haue bin changed into Monarchies and kingdomes. The example heereof was ſeene in the nation of the Iewes, at whoſe beginning euen from the tyme of <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Ioſua,</hi> that people was gouerned in the fourme of a Monarchie (for thoſe two were as chiefe gouernours one after another.) Afterwarde in the time of the Iudges was the ſame ſtate chaunged to the fourme of a common weale, for the people were gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:12958:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> by a choſen number of auncients (except in time of warre when God alwayes rayſed vp to them a Captayne (which they called their iudge.) But againe in the dayes of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell</hi> it altered from a common wealth to a Monarchie, at whiche time <hi>Saul</hi> was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen King. After that, in the time of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees, it was changed from a Monarchie to a popular ſtate, howbeit, that to ſay the truth, it was a confuſed ſtate, whiche had no manner of forme of good gouernement, and yet afterwarde it returned to the manner of a Monarchie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raign of <hi>Herode</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great, and was laſtly put into the forme of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romane Empire. Likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romanes was gouerned as a Monarchie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the raigne of <hi>Romulus</hi> till y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of <hi>Tarquine</hi> the proud, whoſe pride and euill gouernemente was the cauſe that the ſame ſtate was changed into the forme of a common wealth. In that ſtate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romanes continued vnto the dayes of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> at which time it was ſo corrupted with riot, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice, &amp; ambition (whereof the ciuil warres betweene <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> and betweene <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompei</hi> may be a witneſſe,) that it could not but alter and come agayne to a
<pb facs="tcp:12958:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> Monarchie. Since y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which time that great Romane Monarchie hathe bene piteouſly waſted by the euill gouernmentes of many Emperours. And of the waſt of the ſame, haue bin erected many common wealthes and great kingdomes, as <hi>Fraunce, Spayne, Englande,</hi> and other greater and ſmaller Monarchies. To bee ſhorte, theſe chaunges haue bene ſeene in the ſtate of the Romane Empire, in leſſe than .1500 yeare. <note place="margin">Ceſar de bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo gall. lib. 1 cap. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time of <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> ſtood in the ſtate of ſmall common wealthes, which gouerned themſelues apart the one by the other, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations that they had together to reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge them vpon ſtrangers, as the <hi>Cantons</hi> do at this day. But ambition made them bandie, and make warre eache agaynſte other, to proue whiche ſhoulde be the greateſt. Of whome, when they of <hi>Autun</hi> had gotten the vpper hand as the ſtronger, thoſe of <hi>Sequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois</hi> their neighbours, feeling them ſelues the weaker, called the <hi>Almaines</hi> to their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors againſt them of <hi>Autun.</hi> The <hi>Almaines</hi> comming downe vnder the conduct of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſtus,</hi> ſerued them and occupied a good part of the countrie <hi>Sequanois</hi> for their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> They of <hi>Autun</hi> on the other ſyde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſuccor of the <hi>Romanes:</hi> wherevppon <hi>Caeſar</hi> came into <hi>France,</hi> and vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to ſuccour them of <hi>Autun,</hi> and to chace <hi>Arioniſtus</hi> from the countrie that he occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: he wonne to himſelfe the whole countrie of <hi>France.</hi> So as it may truely be ſayd, that that change of the Frenche ſtate happened through the diuiſion that then was in <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> without the which deuiſion, <hi>Caeſar</hi> had neuer vanquiſhed them (what <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſoeuer he had bin.) And truely we ſee by the hiſtories, that alwayes till then, the Frenchmen had well canuaſſed the <hi>Romanes,</hi> yea and taken and burned <hi>Rome.</hi> In ſomuch that (as ſayth <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt</hi>) <note place="margin">Saluſt de bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo Iugurthino</note> the <hi>Romanes</hi> ſo feared them, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes when they hearde the Frenche (to be in armes, yong, and old, prieſtes, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, none excepted or excuſed amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) were commaunded to arme them. Yea, they would openly confeſſe, that againſt all other nations they warred for the gaining of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and glory, but ageinſt the French men, for the preſeruation of their liues. But <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> finding them in deuiſion, added oyle to the flame of their furie, partly by whiche po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> and partly by his valiancie he ſet vppon them, and ouercame them, changed their ſtate from ſundry common wealthes, to one only Monarchie. <note place="margin">Plutarch in Caeſare.</note> Yea, thus muche more hee did, that as with the Romane power, he va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed the Frenchmen, ſo with the French mens money, he obteyned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire (another very good policie) for with the money that he gate in Fraunce, he corrupted the chiefe of Rome, through the fauour of whome, he was choſen <hi>Dictatour</hi> perpetual, which is as much to ſay as Monarch of the Romanes. So was the Realme of France by <hi>Caeſar</hi> vnited to the Romane Empire, from the whiche they often after ſoughte to cutte them ſelues off, as in the ende they did. In the tyme of the Emperour <hi>Tiberius,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cor. Tacitus Annal.</note> one <hi>Iulius Sacrouir</hi> of <hi>Autun</hi> made parte of Fraunce to reuolt, rayſing certayne ſmall aſſemblies ſecretely in the Townes, and exhorting the people, no longer to ſuffer neyther the continuaunce of the tributes (wherewith the Emperour oppreſſed them) nor the pride and crueltie wherewith the Magiſtrates (ſente thyther from Rome) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerburdened them. Alſo they reuolted vnder
<pb facs="tcp:12958:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Emperour <hi>Nero,</hi> as well for his greate crueltie, as for his ouercharging them wyth greate paymentes of money (by mee before ſpoken of.) Lykewiſe vnder the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Gallien</hi> for hys greate riot and whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <note place="margin">Trel. Pollio in Gallienno.</note> as before I haue touched. For the Frenchmen (ſayeth <hi>Pollio</hi>) were in thoſe dayes of ſuche diſpoſition, as they coulde not abide a vicious Prince. And agayne, after they reuolted from the Emperoures, <hi>Probus, Diocleſian,</hi> and others, tyll they hadde quite cut off them ſelues agayne from the Empyre, and politiquely broughte their countrie into a ſelf ſettled Monarchie, the which the Lord long mayntayne.</p>
               <p>Who ſoeuer woulde take vppon him the diſcouering of the infinite number of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, whiche touche the alterations that haue happened in publique eſtates, from Monarchies into common weales, and from common weales into Monarchies (when corruption hadde once caughte them) ſhoulde neuer make an ende: but to mee it ſuffiſeth to haue touched theſe fewe, to the ende that youre Maieſtie by youre wiſedome myghte prouide, that
<pb facs="tcp:12958:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> the corruptions, whiche are nowe crept into <hi>France,</hi> and are dayly like to creepe further, bring not with them a change to the ſtate (which God forbid.) For truely there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that more foreſheweth the alteration of an eſtate, than when corruption is ſeene to ſpread ouer farre into it. I knowe well that men can not be without faultes, neyther can Monarchies, nor common wealthes, bee ſo gouerned, as there may not in the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be found matter of reproofe, but when al things in the fame are to be ſeene turned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpſide downe, when vice is made vertue, and vertue made vice, when good men are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and euill men aduanced: in ſumme, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corruption hath recouered the higheſt degree that it may reache to: then may it well bee ſayd, (according as men do ſee continually) that an exchange of ſtate approcheth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall is to be noted, that by the ordinarie courſe of worldly things, no one ſtate can endure for euer. And ſyr, ſeeing that your kingdome hath endured this twelue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth yeeres and more, you ought ſo muche the rather to feare, leaſt in the ſtate thereof, ſome alteration ſhoulde happen. And if in
<pb facs="tcp:12958:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Iulius Caeſars</hi> time the ſtrangers drawen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fraunce coulde fynde the way to winne the ſame: it is not to bee doubted but if it may lye in their power they will nowe doe the lyke. The Frenchmen, when they ſawe the euill dealing of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> repented their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him into Fraunce, but then it was too late. Let vs therefore in tyme bee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the harmes of our aunceſtours, ſo to prouide for our ſafeties, as we be not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken as were the <hi>Troyans</hi> whiche became wiſe, but not til after ſuch time as they were vtterly ouerthrowen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <head>The ſeconde point.</head>
               <p>HItherto I haue (I thinke) ſufficientlye ſpoken of the firſte poynte of my treatie, that is to ſaye, that a Prince ſhall not fynde profitable, his making of warres agaynſte his ſubiects. It foloweth now, that I come to ſay ſomewhat of the ſeconde, whiche en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of thoſe miſeries that ciuill warres do engender, and the profit that a good peace might bryng to youre Crowne, and poore Subiects.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12958:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Of the calamities that from ciuil warres do proceede, we neede not to make any long diſcourſe, eache ſeeing and feeling the ſame in a thouſand ſortes of afflictions, touchyng their perſons, loſſe of goodes, and deathe of parents and friends, and each knoweth (that hath any iudgemente) the miſchiefes thereof to be ſuch, as wil (if they continue) bring the realme to vtter deſtruction. For ther is none (that ſeeth what we ſee, and knoweth what wee knowe) but may thinke, that (the ciuill warres enduring) it will happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto <hi>France</hi> as it happened to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two fighting Frogges, whiche when they had fought till they were weery, were by the Kyte that came to parte them (in eache foote one) carried away. And it is not to bee doubted, but the ſtraungers whiche to that warre encouraged vs, are as gladde to ſee vs togither by the eares, as was the Kyte ſoaring (ouer the Frogges to ſee them fyght, whoſe fyghting he meant to make a furderaunce to his pray) as they hope ours ſhall one daye bee to theirs, when wee ſhall bee vnable any longer to mayntayne warres. And therefore it is, that ſome on the one ſyde, and ſome on the other, to the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> proceeding on both ſydes, gyue ſo great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragemente. Ah Syr (ſayth one) will you loſe the glorious title of moſt Chriſtian King heeretofore gotten by youre aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, through their maineteyning of the Romane Churche? Will you ſir (cryeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother) ſuffer your Subiectes to preſcribe lawes vnto you, and to bring into youre Realme a newe Religion maugre youre will? will not you perfourme the agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the holy league, whiche is to aboliſhe whatſoeuer in fayth is contrary to the holy Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> The Frenchmen haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foretime had this honor, to haue often paſſed the mountaynes, and to haue made beyonde the ſeas many iourneyes for the defence of the catholique religion, &amp; holy ſea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and muſt they now loſe that glory? <hi>Philip Auguſt</hi> king of <hi>France,</hi> ouerthrew the <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geois</hi> his ſubiects, &amp; made of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great ſlau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they would haue intruded into their countrey a new kinde of Religion, which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was put away &amp; aboliſhed. Why folow you not then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good king your predeceſſour? Theſe &amp; ſuch other proper deuiſes put forth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spanyards &amp; Popes
<pb facs="tcp:12958:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> Pencionaries, to encourage you to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on fire the foure corners (yea and middle parte) of your Realme. But in the meane ſeaſon, none dothe ſaye vnto you. Sir, you ſpyll, and vtterly ſpoyle youre Realme, in making warre againſt your ſubiects, whych kind of warre, no Prince did euer finde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytable. There is none that ſayth vnto you, Sir, you bring your ſelfe in hatred of youre neighbours the <hi>Almaines, Engliſhmen, Scots</hi> and <hi>Flemings,</hi> from whom in time of neede more amitie might be drawen than may ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Italians or Spaniardes. None dare to you ſay, Sir, this cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is not yet ſo broughte out of doubte, that the goſpellers be vanquiſhed in the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of their fayth: for they preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues at <hi>Poiſsi,</hi> in the time of your late bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to mainteine the poyntes of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but my maiſters the Prelates, were as then at no leyſure to confute them: ſo that whether in fayth they erre or not, is as yet vndetermined. And therefore you ſhoulde not be ſo greatly moued as to execute them before they were condemned. And touchyng the councell of <hi>Trent</hi> they ſay, it is as it were
<pb facs="tcp:12958:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> a determined ſentence giuen of a ſelfwil, and that they ought neuertheleſſe to be hearde, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt in purging themſelues of ſtubborne dealing, as in deede they may well doe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, there are that beate downe the ſayd counſell as a thing of no force, as the late maſter <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Molin</hi> a very lerned law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer doth, who hath taken .xxx. or fortie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions to the ſaide counſell. And there are ſome of opinion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men ought to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to haue a writ of error againſt the ſame counſell, as wel as againſt a wrong iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> giuen vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearing of the parties. Wherefore to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the poore goſpellers &amp; to roote them out by peremptorie iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before they be duly condemned, and their reaſons and defences herd, were too wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gful &amp; vnreaſonable dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſeeing that ouerhaſtie iudgements are not vſed in leſſer matters. Yea but (ſay they) they be rebellious and ſeditious, ha, that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother maner of matter. The things that I ſay at this preſent, are but to diſproue the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ſuch as help to kindle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fire in Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnder pretence of rooting out the enimies of the faith, for in that reſpect I ſaye, that that
<pb facs="tcp:12958:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> point is not voyde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Touching that which is ſaid that the goſpellers ſhould be rebels, they flatly denie it: put the caſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> it cannot be denied but they haue theſe be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bin compelled by ſundry greate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> yet wer it no hard matter, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to reduce them to obedience.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which ſo ſound y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trumpet, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vs to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warrs, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtaying of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, care not much by what makes they do it, ſo it be don. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at, is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we deſtroy ourſelues with our owne proper forces, a thing to them ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>end, ſo it be done without their coſt. The Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes ſtande in hope to become greates, by our becomming leſſe, and would gladly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>Spayne</hi> with the lowe countrie. &amp; they could (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gayning of <hi>France</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene both.) And the potentates of Italy know very well, that were the Frenchmen once at reſt, they would by and by vndertak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome voyages thither, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> recouerie of the realmes of <hi>Cycill, Naples,</hi> and the Dutchy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Millaine,</hi> as did the late kings of happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie <hi>Charles</hi> the eight, <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth, <hi>Frauncis</hi> the firſte, and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeconde.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be further the like part and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the doing in as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, not to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Henry</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirde wherwith alſo, they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n feare, leaſt vnder the colour of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ages, Italy will one day be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to crye <hi>liberty, liberty,</hi> if they ſhal once ſee ſuche mother King in <hi>Fraunce</hi> as was Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ght. So take they pleaſure to ſee vs at warre whilſt they as lookers on lye at their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in peace. But doth they and we (it we did wel) ſhould more aduiſedly looke to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter, than eyther to runne one vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, or to nouriſh ciuill diuetio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt our ſelues. For within little more than .80. yeeres, the Turk hath taken <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> from the Chriſtians, &amp; ſince he neuer ceaſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enlarging of his limites vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dom, aſwel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Iland of <hi>Rhodes</hi> &amp; <hi>Cipres,</hi> as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land of <hi>Hungary</hi> &amp; other places. And di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our deuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, he worketh his adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, wherof may beare good witnes the priſes by him of late taken at the <hi>Goletta</hi> &amp; at <hi>Tunis,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ouerthrow of the Spanyardes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through he hath made open the paſſages for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enbarquing of himſelfe at his pleaſure, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into <hi>Spayne, Cicill, Italy, Marcelles</hi> or <hi>Narbone,</hi> without any ſtoppe or ſtay. And
<pb facs="tcp:12958:51"/> might he once enter into Italy (as god forbid he ſhuld) it were greatly to be feared that he woulde make him ſelfe Pope, with a ſhorte roabe. Wherefore holye Saint Peeter might do wel to looke to his own buſines, &amp; rather to ſolicite matter of peace to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mayntayn in Fraunce ſuch ciuill warres as is lyke to conſume the ſtrength of that Realm, which might in time to come be a neceſſary neighbour for Italies defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
               <p>But are not wee maruelouſly blinded in our paſſions? For thoſe my maſters the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates of Italie which haue their factours in Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of great credit, are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe means, that we with ciuill warres are entertayned, taking pleaſure to ſee vs buckle togither, no more nor leſſe than did the auntiente Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, when in their theatres they ſawe the ſword players kill the one the other. This was a kind of paſtime accuſtomed to be ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed to the people, who tooke greate pleaſure to behold ſuch cruel ſpectacles (ſo full of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety they wer) &amp; euer accuſtomed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of bloud. And truly we Frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are now become y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ſucceſſors to thoſe aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Romanes (ſucceſſors I ſay to their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:12958:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> not their vertues) in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſing our ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters &amp; deſperate ſkyrmiſhes as ſportes &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes to pleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withall. I will not ſay holy S. Peter himſelfe reioiceth in the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of french bloud, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were an errour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth of holy church, after whom we muſt beleeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it can doe, ſpeake, nor thinke any thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is euil: but what was his meaning, in making in Rome ſo greate bonefiers for ioye, and iolly generall proceſſions in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere 1572. in September, vpon the ariuall of the newes of the Bartholmew conſpiracie?</p>
               <p>To conclude vpon this poynt, certaine it is, that our ciuill warres (if they continue,) will bring muche pleaſure and paſtime to ſtrangers (and it may be, much profite to) but not without our preiudice and vtter deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For what other may we looke for, than that thoſe of vs which ſhall happen to eſcape the ſworde (be they Catholikes, be they Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers) ſhal not eſcape famine and thoſe that eſcape famine, it may be, ſhall not eſcape the hande of the ſtrange enimie, to whome they muſt then become ſeruants and ſlaues. Then will they lament thoſe deade in the warres, wiſhing for death and can not dye. Beſides
<pb facs="tcp:12958:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> this ſyr, your Maieſtie can not looke after ought elſe, than reuolts, rebelloins diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, hatred of ſubiects, and laſtly, the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine and ouerthrowe of your eſtate, (whiche God forbid.) And whyleſt theſe miſchiefes are in hand (and before the ſtorme come) you ſhal reape none other fruites than diſpleaſures, heauineſſe, deſpites, angers, treaſons, troubles, and ſuche like that may hinder the health of your perſon, wherewith alſo ye muſt taſte part of the peoples pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that will not or can not ſo fully furniſhe you with money, as the neceſſitie of your caſe ſhall require.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe, is there not occaſion to feare ſome perticular daunger? <hi>Childerick</hi> kyng of Fraunce, for hauing onely offended a meane Gentleman named <hi>Bandille,</hi> whome he cauſed to be ſcourged, was ſlayne in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh by him. What became of it? <hi>Bandille</hi> was not ſomuch as once ſerched for by <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericks</hi> ſucceſſor, and as touching the fact, it was eſteemed as a thing well done, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging ſuch an iniurie. And the gentleman was for that deede commended by the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, as he was alſo of <hi>Ronſard,</hi> where he ſpeaketh of the king <hi>Childerick,</hi> thus:
<pb facs="tcp:12958:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>The King vnable for to rule</l>
                     <l>him ſelfe through heate of wrath.</l>
                     <l>The valiant Knight ſyr <hi>Bandil</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>to a poſt laſt tyed hath</l>
                     <l>In publike place, and cauſing him</l>
                     <l>ſtarke naked to be ſtript,</l>
                     <l>From top to toe moſt cruelly</l>
                     <l>with paſſing rage him whipt.</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Bandil</hi> ſtout and fierce of minde,</l>
                     <l>conceyuing more diſdayne</l>
                     <l>Of ſo outrageous villanie,</l>
                     <l>than paſſing for the payne:</l>
                     <l>And feeding in his penſiue hart</l>
                     <l>on purpoſe to requite,</l>
                     <l>Will wiſely for a time let ſlip</l>
                     <l>the wreaking of that ſpite.</l>
                     <l>But afterward (the ſhamefulneſſe</l>
                     <l>ſo ſore his hart doth ſting)</l>
                     <l>He burning in diſdaine and rage</l>
                     <l>againſt the cruell king.</l>
                     <l>And hauing no regard at all</l>
                     <l>of ſcepter, crowne, or ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Will pay him home his haſtie mode</l>
                     <l>with ſtroke of blouddy fate:</l>
                     <l>His hart will neuer be at reſt</l>
                     <l>vntill his hand haue ſhed</l>
                     <l>His lord and maiſters bloud, and wrought</l>
                     <l>reuengement on his head.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And is it not to be preſumed, that there be at this day a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Bandils,</hi> which feel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as much offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded as he did, your maieſtie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuering in the taking away of their goods
<pb facs="tcp:12958:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> and liues? And ſhall ye not as readily finde <hi>Ronſards</hi> to prayſe and ſet them forwarde in ſuch enterpriſes? Be there not nowe alſo Magiciens that can torment (and by little &amp; little) conſume a body by his image or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait, as well as were in the time of <hi>Valens</hi> and <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperours? Yes, this worlde is at this day more poyſoned with Magitiens, Enchauntours, and Sorcerers, than it was theſe fiue hundred yeeres paſt. But theſe <hi>Hugonots</hi> (will ſome ſay) be of too good conſcience, to vſe thoſe kynde of people. I anſwere therevnto, that there be of diuers ſortes, ſome haue a right good conſcience, and ſome none at all. There be wiſe, there be foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: there be ſufferers, &amp; there be reuengers: but moe without compariſon out of order, than reformed. And be there not numbers alſo of Catholikes not contented: and of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts</hi> not ſatiſfied: which will make ſmall ſcruple, to employ thoſe Magiciens in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging of them ſelues? But to encounter with thoſe enterpriſes, you ſhall do well ſir to take councell of that gentle prince <hi>Arnus,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Porſena</hi> King of the <hi>Hetrurians. Porſena</hi> in the quarell of another (that is to
<pb facs="tcp:12958:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſay) to maynteine the tyrannie of <hi>Tarquin</hi> the proude, vndertooke the warres againſt the Romanes: who ſeeing this King to make them warre, for a thing that nothing touched him, tooke the matter verie haynouſly, in ſo much as there was founde amongſt them, three hundred Gentlemen whiche conſpired to goe in counterfet apparell, to King <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenas</hi> campe, to the ende there to kyll him. <hi>Q. Mutius</hi> was one of the conſpirators, who being come inot the ſaide campe, &amp; ſeing one of the kings ſeruantes ſet in a chayre brauely furniſhed (taking him for the king him ſelf,) killed him with the ſtroke of a dagger: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing giuen this blow, he was taken and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the king, who demaunded of him for what cauſe he had ſo ſlayne his ſeruant: to whome <hi>Mutius</hi> wyth a greate courage (putting his hande into the fire that then preſently there burned) anſwered after this manner. This is the hande that committed the faulte in killing thy ſeruant, where I ment to kyll thee, and therefore it is reaſon it ſuffer the payne due to ſuch deſert. Hereat was none more abaſhed than <hi>Poiſena</hi> him ſelfe, who ſeeing the magnanimitie of this
<pb facs="tcp:12958:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> iolly yong gentleman, commaunded him to be ſet at libertie. <hi>Mutius</hi> who looked for none other than death, ſeeing the Kyngs noble diſpoſition, ſayde vnto him: Sir, for as much as thou haſt towardes me vſed a farre greater clemencie, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I could in any reſpect haue looked for, I wil in reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy goodneſſe, do thee truly to vnderſtand; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are of vs .300. Romane Gentlemen, which haue conſpired thy death, for the preuenting wherof, it ſhal be good that thy guard haue a good eye vnto thee. <hi>Porſena</hi> vpon thoſe words more aſtonyed than before, cauſed an aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of his councell to conſult what guarde he might beſt entertayne, for the keeping of him from thoſe conſpiratours. Amongſt whome the gentle Prince <hi>Arnus</hi> his ſonne, was of opinion that he was not ſo muche to conſider of, what guard he ſhuld vſe, as he was to prouide for his hauing no neede of a guard. Then his father aſked hym how that myght be done: in making (ſayth he) the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes of enimies to become your friendes, which you may, and were beſt to doe, if you make more account of your life, than ye do of the maintenance of <hi>Tarquins</hi> wicked cauſe. The King beleeued his ſonne, made peace
<pb facs="tcp:12958:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> with the Romanes, and departed in ſafetie.</p>
               <p>A number of other miſeries and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that hang on ciuill warres, myght heere be diſcouered, whereof when I thinke, me ſemeth to ſee a <hi>Chimere</hi> or other hideous monſter, accompanyed with all the euils, miſchieſes, and miſeries that are in earth, ſea, or hell, whereof (as of a deteſtable thing) it grieueth me to ſpeake, or once to thinke: neyther woulde I ſerue as a <hi>Noſterdame</hi> to our poore Realme of Fraunce, in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewing of thoſe calamities and deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whiche dayly doe threaten vs (if oure ſayde ciuill warres continue) but had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſtande as a <hi>Ionas,</hi> in praying vnto God for his dealing towardes vs, as hee dealt towardes that great citie <hi>Niniuie,</hi> from whome for one amendment, he turned away the deſtruction before threatned vnto them. we haue already endured miſerie inough, both to make vs wiſe, and to prouoke vs to amendment: if neither wiſdome nor amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment haue folowed thereof, let it nowe doe: It is better late than neuer.</p>
               <p>I wil herevnto adde (as it were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of war) a ſentence of the great Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> worthy by al princes
<pb facs="tcp:12958:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> to be noted. That good Prince was wont to ſay, that warres ſhould neuer be taken in hande, but where hope maketh more ſhewe of profit, than feare can do of loſſe: meaning, where victorie may bring great profite, and vanquiſhment ſmall loſſe: for thoſe (ſayth he) which will ſeeke ſmall profite, and hazarde therefore great loſſe, may well be likened to him that fiſheth with a hooke of golde, which broken off and caryed away, bringeth more loſſe to the fiſher, than much fiſhe can recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence. Let vs a little conſider I pray you ſir, what aduantage may growe to you by van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing all the Goſpellers? is it the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Religion quite out of youre realme? Let it be ſo, yet can you not for all that ſo chaſe it out of the worlde, but that it may after your time returne agayne into Fraunce. And before ye attayne to that ſmal profite, ye are like inough to loſe (what of your nobles and of your commons) an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of Catholikes, as the late king your brother, in his warres late paſſed (the more is the pitie) hath done. For let it be counted a ſmall loſſe, the loſing of ſo many braue Goſpellers, as the curteous and right
<pb facs="tcp:12958:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> noble <hi>Lewes</hi> of <hi>Burbon,</hi> Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> the valiaunt <hi>Dandalot,</hi> the wiſe <hi>Admirall,</hi> the good Count <hi>Rochfoucault,</hi> the honeſt <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligni,</hi> the braue captaines <hi>Bruoquemauds</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſonne, <hi>Pilles, Monius,</hi> the <hi>Pardil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans,</hi> with a number of like other. Yea let the Bartholmewe iourney be reckoned for a braue politike exployre (although the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers ſo confeſſeth not) but doe rather in their Almanackes macke that feaſte wyth blackt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, in token of heauyneſſe, ſorow, and blot euerlaſting. Where me thinkes if rather deſerued to haue dwelte in red let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in remembrance, that the ſame day all Fraunce was dyed red, wyth the bloude of hir childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And though nothing elſe (I ſay) were to be weyghed, the loſſe of ſo many notable Goſpellers: yet is it nothing to haue ſoft ſo many valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and noble Catholiques? Is it little to haue loſt <hi>Fraunces</hi> of <hi>Lorraine</hi> Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> great maiſter of Fraunce? (verily a good and valiant Captaine, and an <hi>alter <hi>Charles Martel,</hi>
                  </hi> which <hi>Ronſard</hi> thus writeth of.)
<q>
                     <l>Among the frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Martell raignes with fame,</l>
                     <l>As king of kings, though not a king in name.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12958:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Is it nothing to haue loſt the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>d'Aumale</hi> his brother, the luſtie Count <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke,</hi> the curteous Count <hi>Martignes,</hi> wyth a greate number of other, wherethrough there remayneth at this day fewe good ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in Fraunce, (the nobilitie thereof being alſo well next extincte, through theſe in the ciuill warres: yea but ſome maiſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> maye chaunce to ſay, that the nobilitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may ſone be renued, for the Kyng hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer of villaines to make noble men. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> confeſſe that your Maieſtie of ignoble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make noble, ſo farre foorth as to the inioy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of the priviledges of nobilitie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aduau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment of the perſons to great eſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and preheminence: but I beleeue not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a Kyng of a Clowne or baſe artificer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make a noble Gentleman, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zarde or Keſtrell can be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hawke. Nobilitie muſt from nobl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture naturally proceede. And it can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be denyed, but there is commonly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> apparance of generoſitie, in ſuche as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſcended of nobilitie, than in fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lineally proceeded from parentes of mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> degree. For as ſayth <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Each breedes his like the Bull a Bull,</l>
                     <l>the warlike horſe, a horſe:</l>
                     <l>The cruell Eagle breedeth not</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Doue deuoyd of force.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Yet will I not altogether deny, but ſome iſſued out of the meane places, become hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſonages, and are replete with noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vertue, and knowledge, but thoſe are verie rare. And therefore they that to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage you to the proſecuting of the warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your fith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es, ſay, ye may all newe make nobilitie: ſpeake bothe without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and good conſideration, and there ſuche ſpeaches are odious.</p>
               <p>But again to returne to <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar.</hi> It is certaine that in the ciuill warres, as the gaine to be gotten by the vanquiſhing of the goſpellers can (at the beſt hand) be, but ſmal: ſo may the loſſe to growe thereby, be (at the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hand very great, euen to the daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſtate, if it ſhould ſo fal out, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with good policie) ſhould bounde vpper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood: And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a thing not altogether impoſſible, though your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to your late brother haue hitherto had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wars are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iable, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tures
<pb facs="tcp:12958:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the ſame daungerous, ſo as he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this day, is commonly a winner to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe. The <hi>Beniamires</hi> after the ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of their aduerſaries in two ſeuerall battelles, were in the thirde, of the ſame ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries ouercome.</p>
               <p>And I woulde verie fayne aſke of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> counſelled you to the beſieging of <hi>Pouzin,</hi> and <hi>Graue,</hi> howe well they vnderſtoode that ſaying of <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> was not that the right fyſhing with a hooke of golde broken off and loſt? coſt not thoſe two peeces fiftie tymes more than they were worth? neyther <hi>Pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin</hi> nor <hi>Graue,</hi> with al their reuenues, goods, men, women, and children, being ſolde to the vttermoſt farthing, ſhall euer be ſo muche worth. Now coming to entreate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this peace, alas my deſire to ſee it well ſtabliſhed in Fraunce, doth ſo rauiſhe me, as I knowe not at which ende thereof to begin: willingly would I prognoſticate, that like honor and glory ſhould happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Maieſtie (if the Lorde were ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) as in time paſt hapned to <hi>Auguſtus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> who after the ciuill warres were ceaſed in the Romane Empire (wherein him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:12958:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> had bene a partie) ſtabliſhed throughout the ſame a perfect, good, and ſure peace, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſetled the people in reſt and tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Wel, I wil in hope of good hap that may folowe my happy deſire, write this verſe whiche <hi>Horace</hi> ſong in the honour of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus,</hi> and ſo apply it to your Maieſtie.
<q>
                     <l>AS I the deeds of <hi>Mars,</hi> did mynde in meetre for to bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>And of his prayſes to my harpe a dittie for to ſing,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Apollo</hi> did by wordes expreſſe, commaund me for to ceaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>And for to turne my note, to ſing of glad and ioyfull peace:</l>
                     <l>Which thou king <hi>Henrie,</hi> ſhouldſt in <hi>France</hi> eſtabliſh, ſo as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of corne &amp; wine &amp; all good fruits, ſhould plentie haue by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou, thou art he, I ſay, that ſhal the golden age renue,</l>
                     <l>By meanes wherof, immortal fame ſhal vnto thee inſue.</l>
                     <l>The doores of <hi>Ianus</hi> thou ſhalt ſhut: the terror of thy mace</l>
                     <l>All euill and vngracious deeds by holy lawes ſhall chace.</l>
                     <l>And vnder thee all holeſome artes ſhall flouriſh new agein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which in the eaſt ſhal ſpred abroad the honor that doth reig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Within thy royal Maieſtie. So daunted <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> ſhall be,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Henries</hi> reigne, that ciuill warres we neuer more ſhal ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>There ſhall no warre nor trouble be, in field nor yet in tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>His power the frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell, their choller to lay dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which draue them to ſuch miſeries. Al quarters of this lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall humbly and obediently ſubmit them to his hande.</l>
                     <l>Ther ſhal be neither great nor ſmal y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dare once break his he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>To heauen we ſhall aduance his praiſe in quiet peace and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Beſeching God to graunt the houſe of <hi>Valoys</hi> to reteine</l>
                     <l>The royal mace eternally, for aye in <hi>Fraunce</hi> to reigne.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12958:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Many are the commodities ſir, that a good peace might bring to your people, which are (as it were) the huſbands &amp; traders by whoſe meanes your realme might become plentiful in corne, wine, ſiluer, gold, and al other need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, pleaſant, and profitable things: &amp; thereby (thinke I) your ſtate royall ſhould be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly augmented. For the chiefe part of a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces greatneſſe, is the proſperitie and wealth of his ſubiectes (who bring poore, their prince can not be riche,) nexte the whiche a Princes force dependeth vpon his peoples willing obedience, but that render they not ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, when they are oppreſſed with warrs, and want wherewith to furniſhe them, as when they are maynteined in peace, and by their tillage &amp; traffike, haue thoſe wantes ſupplyed.</p>
               <p>And ſurely the money that mainteyneth theſe vnhappy warres, employed vpon the entertaynment of ſtraungers, and liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſtowed vppon the well affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you, woulde purchaſe you no ſmall ſtrength.</p>
               <p>And might the <hi>Polonians</hi> once vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that your Maieſtie had eſtabliſhed a
<pb facs="tcp:12958:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> perfecte good peace in Fraunce, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of the profeſſours of both the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions: as it is not to be doubted, but they woulde yeelde you muche the more affection and obedience: ſo is it to bee feared, if it ſhould otherwyſe fall out, that they wil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them of ſome other king. And ſomuch the rather for that their late king <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> did alwayes maynteine them, not onely in good peace, but alſo in the exerciſe of bothe the religious, the altering of their libertie wherein, can not but be to them a thing both newe and troubleſome.</p>
               <p>The Almaines alſo (which amongſt them ſelues for Religion haue had great warres, and by whoſe harmes we might learne, that force and violence, hath not power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the conſcience, (the guiding whereof is to be lefte to God onely) are people that woulde greatly eſteeme of you ſyr, if once they vnderſtoode that you had in Fraunce framed a peace to the lyking of bothe the Relygions. Yea they woulde be ſo glad of your neyghborhood, as ye myght and ſhould commaunde their friendſhips in any neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of war. A commoditie of no ſmall value
<pb facs="tcp:12958:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> conſidering that Almaine is the ſtorehouſe of ſouldiers, whereout may be leuyed armie vpon armie, without diſfurniſhment of the countrey, that neuer can be made barren of men of warre.</p>
               <p>And when I conſider the ſmall number of Chriſtian Princes that liue in theſe dayes, wherein y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour is alreadie decaying: and that the lawe of creating Emperours, called <hi>(Le bulle doree)</hi> forbiddeth the choſing of any moe than foure Emperours toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of one houſe, and howe there haue bene diuers of the houſe of Auſtriche, (as <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, Frederike, Maximilian, Charles</hi> the fift, <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> and <hi>Maximilian,</hi> nowe raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) choſen one after another: Me thinkes there is no prince in the worlde, that might better aſpire to the Empire than your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. But to bring the ſame to paſſe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loueth you to winne the loue and fauour of the Almaines, whiche ye can no way better do, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erecting of a good peace in your realme, plauſible to both religious, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe whereof, they now both gouerne &amp; are gouerned, and haue their chamber compoſed of perſons profeſſing the one and the other.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> True it is that bothe the ſayde Religions through out all <hi>Almaigne</hi> be not vſed, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ther are not in all places people of both ſortes, ſome place conſiſting of goſpellers, and ſome of Catholiques: but in places where people of both be, both religions are exerciſed. If it then pleaſed God, that youre maieſtie might come to be emperour (as that way yee might eaſily do) was there euer ſo great a king of <hi>France</hi> as you ſhoulde then be? mighte yee not then march from one of your Realmes to another though they bee 200. leagues aſunder, ſtill in your owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions? And (hauing the forces of <hi>Almaine</hi> at commaundement, with thoſe of both your realmes) ſhould there Moſkouite or Turke be comparable to youre greatneſſe? Some will anſweare me and ſaye, that the Turke is a mightie and a puiſſant gouernour, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnder his obeyſance, many realmes and prouinces. I frankly confeſſe it, but I reply therevnto as did <hi>Quintius</hi> a generall of the Romane army to the vaunting and bragging meſſengers of King <hi>Antiochus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This king was a great and mighty mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narque in the Eaſt, who lacked little of the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> Turke in the enlargeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his dominions. His Ambaſſadours willing to feare thys braue Captayne <hi>Quintius,</hi> and thereby to make him retire out of <hi>Greece,</hi> (where hee was,) ſayd vnto him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their maſter brought towardes him an infinite number of people, all well expert in warre, paſſing well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, and ſuch as ſhot on horſeback. And the more to aſtoniſhe him, they named vnto him diuers ſortes of nations to be in <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> campe, ſome of the which this Captain <hi>Quintius</hi> had neuer heard named before (as <hi>Dahans, Elimeens, Caduſiens</hi> &amp; ſuche others. Adding further that hee ſhoulde not haue to do with <hi>Hanniball</hi> of <hi>Carrhage,</hi> nor yet with king <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedony,</hi> but with the greateſt part of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europa.</hi> Well (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Quintius</hi>) I will ſay vnto you, that youre talke putteth mee in minde of a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, whiche mine hoſt of <hi>Chalchis</hi> (a good companion) once made me. I being hys gueſt in the Sommer time when the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was very hote, greatly maruelled from whence hee had gotten the ſundrye ſortes of veniſon, wherewith we were ſerued. Vppon which my maruelling, this good felowe (that
<pb facs="tcp:12958:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> vaunted not as you doe) began for to laugh, confeſſing all thoſe diuerſities of ſeruices, to haue bin made of a tame ſwine, but dreſſed with varietie of ſawces. Euen ſo (ſaid he) all thoſe ſortes of people which you haue nowe named with diuers names, are all but <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> for all theyr ſundry names. Commyng agayne to my purpoſe, I ſay, that all thoſe Nations vnder the Turkes obeyſance, bee all but Eaſterlings, betweene whome and the weſterne people, touching their men of warre, there is a great difference. For al the hiſtories beare witneſſe, that thoſe of the Weſt, with their ſmall numbers haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vanquiſhed them of the Eaſt with their greate numbers, as appeareth by the warrs which the Romanes haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If it bee replyed to me that the Turkes bee at thys daye more valiaunt, than were the auncient nations of the eaſt, as being iſſued out of the warlike nations, inhabiting the South, I wil therevnto anſweare, and that by two reaſons. The one is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> how warlike ſoeuer the Turkes are ſuppoſed to be: they haue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch oft times bin va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhed, as in the voiage which they made into <hi>Leuant</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnder <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Greece, India,</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe with their confines, euen to the mount <hi>Taurus.</hi> And not only ſo conquered thoſe countries, but alſo them ſelues, and theyr ſucceſſors raigned ouer them .26. yeeres, in the ende whereof, thoſe ſucceſſors fell in deuiſion and banded the one againſte the other, and by that occaſion they were all expulſed thence. My other reaſon is, that it is very likely that the Turkes ſince they came from the South partes to dwell in <hi>Greece,</hi> and other the Eaſt countries: are muche degenered from their naturall and firſte nobleneſſe, as were the French that ſometime went to dwel in that part of Greece, which after was called <hi>Gallo Grecia.</hi> For the firſte that went thither were ſo braue, ſo valiant, and ſo warlike a people, as they not onely enioyed the countrie at their pleaſure, but by their vertues and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances kept in awe all the kings and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries that were round about them, ſo far foorth, as they were glad to yeeld them tribute, for the enioying of their fauours. But in proceſſe of time, that race ſo degenered, as <hi>Attalus</hi> a King in <hi>Aſia</hi> firſt refuſed the paiment of the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> tribute by his predeceſſors before payed, by whom (when they had long therefore aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him with warre,) they were in the ende ouercome: and after that they became euery daye more cowardly than other, ſo as they were againe vanquiſhed by the Romanes vnder the conduct of Captayn <hi>Manlius.</hi> And what ſhould let your maieſtie from doyng as much as did ſometime thoſe of the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch nation, vnder the conduct of that ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> of <hi>Bulloigne?</hi> Seeing that the people of that countrie (namely the Greekes,) deſire nothing more than their cutting off from their obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the Turke, which is a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous tyrant, enimie to all lawes, godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, knowledge, yea &amp; to learning, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that countrie of Greece was wont to bee the nouriſhing mother. It is alſo well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, that the King of <hi>Moſcouia</hi> is a very cruell tyrant, and ſo cruelly and barbarouſly reigneth ouer his ſubiectes, as they woulde moſt gladly be vnyoked from his ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Of other countries of Chriſtendome I ſpeake not, leauing for euery man of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente to thinke, whether welneere anye thing ſhall be impoſſible to your maieſtie,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> hauing linked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forces of your two realms with thoſe of <hi>Almaine,</hi> and eſpecially when your gouernement ſhall be fauourable and agreeable to youre ſubiectes; wherethrough alſo other nations will become deſirous to ſubmit them ſelues to your obeyſance.</p>
               <p>We read that <hi>Charlemain</hi> your predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour was ſo wiſe &amp; ſo good a prince, that all Italy deſired him for their Lorde. And it came to paſſe, that (by the meanes of that good liking which the world had of him) hee was choſen Emperour. <hi>Xenophon</hi> writeth, that <hi>Cirus</hi> the greate Monarche in <hi>Leuant,</hi> was ſo gentle &amp; modeſt in his gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thoſe nations that neuer ſawe (but had one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y heard ſpeaking of him,) deſired to becomes his ſubiects, and this propertie he had, that he woulde leaue to euery nation their lawes, cuſtomes, liberties, and religions, without chaunging in the ſame any thing contrary to their conſentes, which the <hi>Greekes</hi> called in one word <hi>Autonomie.</hi> The graunting of which, hath alwayes bin and is the very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way to walke in for any Prince y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would either gaine any ſtrange natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or winne the harts of his own ſubiecte. So vſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>der</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> the great his conqueſts, contenting himſelfe with the ſoueraigntie ouer thoſe nations which he ſubdued, without altering of theyr eſtates, or forcing of their religions. The like whereof vſed the aunciente Romanes, when vnder their gouernment they brought any nation, for they willingly altered not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of the countries which they conquered, nor forced the people to the receyt of theyr lawes or religion, if they made any change, it was in diminiſhing the tributes for the drawing vnto them the loue of the people. and <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> did euen ſo in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſts of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> for hee altered nothing of the ſtates of thoſe Cities whiche hee conquered, but vſed them with as muche curteſie and gentleneſſe, as he poſſible might. If any ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie rebelled, by gentle meanes he ſoughte to reduce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder his obedience. And though he was oft conſtrayned to fetche them in by force, he vſed not (being victour) his victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cruelly, but was alwayes enclined to pardoning. To the vnfaythfull he forbare the rendring of vnfaythfulneſſe, as one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> woulde take no example of his aduerſaries<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And of a trueth, there was
<pb facs="tcp:12958:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> nothing more furthered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Alexander, Cyius,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and ſuche other greate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han did the graunt of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> little care tooke the people for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſiſtance, when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſubmitted, they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caſes ſhoulde rather be much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhall any whit app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed. The <hi>Switch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> day with muche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> entreat their ſubiects, ſaying; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger caſtels nor more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, than thoſe ſhal bee builded within the hands of the ſubiects.</p>
               <p>Who ſo woulde take vpon him the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rring at large of the greate benefites, that a good peace would bring to your crowne and poore ſubiects, might find mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to fill a great volume: but I ſhall contente mee with what before is ſaide, adding only thys vnto it, that in hauing a good peace, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhall ſhunne all the miſchiefes and miſeries that warres alwayes bring with them &amp; though there grewe therevpon none other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, yet were the ſame alone ſufficiente to moue you to the procuring of peace. Whych
<pb facs="tcp:12958:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> grace fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of your<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> people. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> happy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> warres, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> good and perd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> peace throughout the Empire of <hi>Romes</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="point">
               <head>The thirde poynt.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſteth nowe that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ate vppon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> point, of the which I ſay, that it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not ſo muche impoſſible to eſtabliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as many iudge it to be for the better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I will firſt anſwer to the difficulties whiche therein are alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. It is ſayde that a peace cannot be made throughout all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> withoute the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of both the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> bycauſe it holdeth the Subiectes, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>alities and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſion. I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tentedly confeſſe that pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nnot otherwiſe be made, but I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it to be a thing inſufferable.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12958:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The <hi>Turkes</hi> by their <hi>Alcaron,</hi> are bounde to become perpetuall ſworne enimies to the Chriſtians, and to deteſt Ieſus Chriſte, in denying hym to be God, to reiect the holy Trinitie, neyther may they beleeue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures of the Bible: and they neuer crowne Emperoure but they ſolemnelye ſweare him to continuall warre with the Chriſtians. All the which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, the Great <hi>Turke,</hi> doth ſuffer the Chriſtians vnder his obeyſance to enioy theyr Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein (paying their tributes) they liue peaceably without controlement or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure of the people. And euery man ſeeth the Turquiſh Religion, to be much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Catholiques, than is that of the Goſpell. For the Goſpellers acknowledge Ieſus Chriſte for God and man, and to bee the mediatour betweene God his Father and men: they allow of the Trinitie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures of the Bible. Yea they agree with the Catholiques, in the Articles of the Fayth. Wherefore then ſhoulde theſe two religions bee inſufferable (the Catholiques and the <hi>Turkes</hi> being togither tollerable.)</p>
               <p>The Iewiſh Religion was and is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch
<pb facs="tcp:12958:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> contrary to that of the <hi>Painims,</hi> for neuer did nation ſo much deteſt images and numbers of Goddes, as dyd the Iewes, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that they haue had and yet haue: (an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of Ceremonies perticular to them ſelues) and contrariwiſe the Paganes haue had an infinite number of Gods with their temples full of images, and their cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and traditions cleane contrary to thoſe of the Iewes. And is there not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt all the nations of the <hi>Painims</hi> (as <hi>Greekes, Parthians, Medes, Elamites, Meſopotamians</hi> and generally throughout all the Eaſt and Weſt peoples,) Sinagogues of the Iewes? Yea, and it is lawfull to the <hi>Painims</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whome they dwell) to make them ſelues Iewes, after the which done, they are called by the name of <hi>Proſelites.</hi> We reade alſo of diuers Romane Emperours, (aſwel <hi>Painims</hi> as Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) which haue ſuffered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iews to dwel vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obeyſance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as <hi>Nerua, Antonius Pius, Conſtantine, Theodoſe, Valentinian, Gratian, Honorius, Arcadius, Iuſtinian</hi> &amp; other. <note place="margin">Dion in Nerua ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitolinus in An Putat C. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deis &amp; Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic.</note> And at this day, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Pope,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Venetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> many townes of <hi>Italy</hi> &amp; <hi>Almaine,</hi> ſuffer ſinagogs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes vnder
<pb facs="tcp:12958:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> obeyſance, and yet is the Iewiſh Religion muche more contrarie to the Catholiques, than is that of the Goſpellers. Some perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture will ſay, that the French men wyll not ſuffer any Iewes in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> but haue alwayes expulſed them. I confeſſe that they haue ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed them away, yet not for matters of religion, but partly for their cruelties committed vpon yong children (whom they robbed from the Chriſtians,) as the hiſtories make mention, and eſpecially for the hatred that they bare to their vſuries: wherevppon they yet vſe this prouerbe, when any is noted for a great vſurer, <hi>He is in vſury a very Iewe.</hi> Vpon the whiche occaſion alſo the Italians heeretofore called <hi>Lombards</hi> (whiche with their great vſuries did robbe (as ſtill they do) the realme of the treaſure) haue bin chaſed out of <hi>Fraunce.</hi> In the beſt townes whereof (yea and that in the very harte of the ſame where diuers ſtreetes and places, yet beare the names of <hi>Iewries</hi>) the Iewes ſhuld now dwell at their eaſe (as well as euer they did) were there none other matter to let them than their onely religion, whiche (though it bee muche contrary to that of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques)
<pb facs="tcp:12958:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> was neuer the cauſe of their chaſing out of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> where before their expulſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, they hadde dwelte many hundred yeeres.</p>
               <p>Neyther can it bee denied, that the <hi>Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims</hi> Religion is cleane contrary to that of the Catholiques, and yet haue diue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim Emperours ſuffered as many as wold, to become Chriſtians vnder them, as <hi>Nerua, Anthonius Pius,</hi> and <hi>Alexander Seuerus.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dion i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nerua. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio. Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pridius in Alexandro.</note> 
                  <hi>Traian</hi> alſo did ſecretly ſuffer them likewiſe to do withoute any ſearch made after them. And thoſe Emperours dyd not ſo in reſpecte of any good thyng they founde in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, the profeſſors whereof they beleeued to be the wickeddeſt people in the worlde, in ſomuche as among the Paynim people, the only name of Chriſtian was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted and abhorred, witneſſe heereof <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> whych called the Chriſtians, men of a newe (and malitious) ſuperſtition. And <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſayd, that the people vſed the name of Chriſtian as a matter of mockery and deriſion, the profeſſours whereof were ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bycauſe of their wickedneſſe. Wherein <hi>Suetonius</hi> and <hi>Tacitus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Suetonius in Nerone Cap. 16. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. lib. 15</note> ſhewed them ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:12958:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> good courtiers, taking pleaſure with lying to pleaſe the princes and the people. <hi>Pliny</hi> the ſeconde, though hee was a <hi>Painim</hi> as they were, and lyued in their time, durſt not lye ſo impudently, but of the liues of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, (to the Emperour <hi>Traian</hi>) rendred a good teſtimonie, as in his Epiſtles is to bee ſeene.</p>
               <p>Seeyng then the <hi>Painim</hi> Emperoures had ſo euill opinion of the chriſtians, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuffered he them to be Chriſtened? Euen for the benefyte of peace? The Emperours <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Maximian</hi> did greatly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Chriſtians, and that of purpoſe, to roote them out, in whyche perſecution they did to deathe an infinite number, but when they ſawe theyr crueltie nothyng to paruayle (but that for euery one they kilde, ten other encreaſed, <hi>Maximian</hi> at the laſt ſuffered, who ſo woulde to become Chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and to exerciſe that Religion. As much myghte bee ſayde of the Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, which did as well deteſt the <hi>Painims</hi> Religion, as dyd the <hi>Painims</hi> that of the Chryſtians, yet woulde they neuer take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb facs="tcp:12958:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> them ſhe conſtraint of their conſciences, but ſuffered to continue <hi>Painims</hi> as many as woulde.</p>
               <p>The Hiſtoriographer <hi>Marcellinus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Am. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellinus libro. 30.</note> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, that the Emperoure <hi>Valentinian</hi> (whyche was a Chriſtian) vſed not to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt any perſon, for matters of Religion, nor euer commaunded that any ſhoulde worſhip eyther this or that, with one faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or other.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe alſo the Emperours <hi>Honorius,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">I. Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis C. de paganis.</note> (whyche were Chriſtians) woulde not that the <hi>Painims</hi> ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be Chriſtened, but cauſed an expreſſe lawe to bee made, that none ſhould offende them, (eyther in their perſons or their goods) vnder the pretence of Religion. If then the Chriſtians haue ſuffered the <hi>Painims</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the <hi>Painims</hi> haue likewiſe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Religion of the Chriſtians. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (to winne peace) will not the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques ſuffer that Religion of the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers? Thoſe two religions haue bin ſeene (ſir) to dwel peaceably togither within your realme of <hi>Poland,</hi> as alſo in many towns of
<pb facs="tcp:12958:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Almaine,</hi> and wherefore ſhould they not as well dwell peaceably togyther in <hi>Fraunce?</hi> Are the French men more hard to be tamed, more diſobediente, or more barbarous and fierce, than other nations? It appeareth cleane contrary. For vpon the Edict of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, the Catholiques were not greeued at all to ſee the Goſpellers vſe the exerciſe of their religion, though it were ſomewhat newe vnto them, but liued the one with the other togither in good peace, wherein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they had till this time continued, if the vnhappy execution of <hi>Vaſsi</hi> (which was the welſpring of all our warres, and of all the miſeries and miſchiefes which we haue ſince that time ſuffered or yet doe ſuffer) had not happened.</p>
               <p>I will not denie, but the warres and acts of hoſtilitie, paſſed betweene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one &amp; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, haue bredde in the hartes of men, hautie minds, &amp; euil diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which may be ſom cauſe, that the Catholiques will now, (more hardly tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the beginning,) ſuffer to come ſo neere them the exerciſe of the Religion: and the rather, for that many eſteeme the ſame Religion to bee the cauſe of all the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſayde miſeries and miſchiefes whiche they feare, would exceede if it ſhoulde againe be reeſtabliſhed in Fraunce. Wherevnto I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that the people of any good iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, are not of that opinion, as thoſe that well knowe (and it is in deede moſt true), that the ambition of ſome, with the deſire they haue to commaunde, and their greedineſſe by the robberie of other to enrich them ſelues, haue bene and are the only cauſes of our troubles, and that there the name of Religion, hath bene vſed but as a cloake or a curtaine to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thoſe pretences. For ſome ſay, they wyll not ſuffer in Fraunce, any other religion tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Catholike, as the moſt auncient, and that hath bene receiued from time out of mynde, ſince the time of great king <hi>Clouis:</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome ſay, they will folowe the religion refourmed, that was not only before <hi>Clouis,</hi> but alſo before the realme of Fraunce: and that they ought not in their conſciences, to be forced: vpon the which controuerſie theſe ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill warres haue bene builded, but the chiefe aduauncers of the cauſe haue had in their hartes another maner of zeale than of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as men of iudgement haue well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued
<pb facs="tcp:12958:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> the common people (which iudge all things raſhly) for that they eſteeme religion to be the cauſe of our warres and calamities, ſtande in feare that (it taking place) the olde woundes woulde breake out and bleede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. This vulgar opinion is not much to be paſſed on, bycauſe it always readily ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the ſtrongeſt parte. But for myne owne part, I beleeue that the beſt part of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, of the commonaltie, yea of the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, for the obtayning of peace, would eaſily conſent that the Goſpel ſhould freely be ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Fraunce, till ſuch time as God (to whome onely the clearing of mans heart by the light of his truth appertayneth) myght knit vs all in one kynde of religion, whiche we are to hope that he (who is the father of knowledge and diſcouerer of all things) will doe, after men ſhall awhyle haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them from the ciuill warres, and caſt quite off th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſtoutneſſe and hatred whiche nowe blindeth their iudgementes. There is at this preſent no order, bycauſe each to the ſide be ſtandeth on, ſticketh faſt each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith to him ſelfe, my religion is good, and I will not ſteppe one foote from it. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:12958:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaith he ſhal I now change my faith and beliefe, ſeeing I haue fought and borne ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in defence of the ſame? Beholde the reaſon men make at this day, of whome ye ſhall haue none other matters. But if their heartes were once a little vnfraighted of their ſtoutneſſe and malice, they ſhoulde all eaſily ſee, that for hauing borne armes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſide, they ſhoulde not forbeare to folowe the trueth, nor willingly ſeeke their owne damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this preſent, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any order to ioyne as in one religion, euerie wiſe man may ſee, that to this point it muſte come, either we muſt nouriſh wars al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> days of our life in Fraunce: or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſuffer the vſe of both the religions, and of two neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the leaſt is to be choſen. For to think that the Goſpellers will be eaſily rooted out, and wholly diſpatched away, it were a meere madneſſe (the experience of xv. yeres hauing ſhewed vs the contrarie.) And the hiſtories beare witneſſe, that often the ſmaller num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber hath ouercome the greater, and that one thouſande ſouldiers (brought into extreame neceſſitie) are many times more worth, than tenne thouſande other. There is ſurely as
<pb facs="tcp:12958:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> much difference betweene murther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the conſeruation of their conſciences, win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> children, and goods, and ſuche as ſight onely for wages: as there is betweene that one wolfe, whiche in his den defending hir yong ones is aſſayled, and that other (whiche ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no yong) through the wood at pleaſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is chaſed.</p>
               <p>Nowe, if ye muſt in Fraunce eyther haue your ciuill warres continued, or both religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſuffered: who ſeeth not of the two, ſuche ſufferances to be moſt expedient? Yea but (ſay they) neyther the people, nor the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie will therevnto agree. I knowe not their mindes nor willes, but I ſhall preſcribe ſuch a reaſonable meane, as woulde eaſily I am ſure; procure their conſentes, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſtraynt: the meane fyr is this. Let your Maieſtie commaunde that patentes be diſpatched to all the communalties of your townes, and to the Chapiters and Colleges of your clergie, wherethrough they may be done to vnderſtande, bowe you are deſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that your realme of Fraunce, ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to reſte and peace, and that the ſame can not be done but by the one way of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:12958:69"/> two, that is, eyther by warre to ouercome and cleane note out all the pretended rebels: or by giuing them peace, with the graunting to them the vſe of their religion. Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your pleaſure, is, that they deliberate in their aſſemblies, and of their reſolute aduices aduer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you, which of thoſe two ways they finde moſte expedient, without vſing in the ſame eyther circumſtance, or any if. And let it further to them be knowne, that ſuche ſhall proſecute the warres againſt the ſayde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended rebel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> at the charges of their townes, communalities, Chapiters, and Colleges:) as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt expedient the folowing of the ſame, from the which charge alſo ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he as for the hauing of peace, are willing to accept the exerciſe of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y thinke ſyr, that vpon the putting foorth of ſuch patentes, all the realme will ſone be ſient to encline them ſelues to peace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>le one being glad rather to accept the exerciſe of that religion (yea within their chiefe and fayreſt Churches) than to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine at their charges a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>te, the ende and victorie whereof is ſo vncertaine. For tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the firſt they can not deny it for a thing
<pb facs="tcp:12958:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> verie reaſonable, that thoſe whiche woulde haue wars, ſhould beare of wars the charge, and thoſe deſirous of peace ſhould from ſuch charge be free: it is a thing ordinarily vſed in the miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of iuſtice, where they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne in coſtes, damages, and intreſtes, ſuch as proſecute any proceſſe to the diffinitiue ſentence, and diſcharge thereof ſuch as in time breake off their ſute: and let it ſo in this caſe he determined, and the charges ariſing to the reſt, will appeare no ſmall portion. For the furniſhing and entertayning of an armie of 25000. footemen, and fiue or ſixe thouſande horſemen, will require no leſſe charge than three hundred thouſande crownes a moneth, which amounteth in the yeere neare to foure Millions of gold. If any ſhal ſay that many ſouldiers will be found which in this warre wil ſerue <hi>gratis,</hi> I can not beleue it, for there are at this day both footmen &amp; horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much grieued for their nonpayments. Wherefore, the beſt they could doe, were firſt to pay thoſe arrearages. And if they ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ordinarie finaunces may beare ſome part of ſuch char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: the contrarie is well knowne, they are otherwiſe beſtowed. For the ſummes
<pb facs="tcp:12958:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> of your reuenue, are no more than ſufficient to the ordinarie entertaynment of the eſtate of your Court, and officers of your crowne: and the money ordinarily rayſed of your tarts and ſubſidies, doth but diſcharge ſo many Garrizons as are this daye in the Realme, whiche in all your good townes and caſtels, muſt of neceſſitie be entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, elſe woulde the pretended rebelles with ſome of them be at hoſte. The ordinarie treaſure of your fynaunces then being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe employed: it ſhall be neceſſarie, that my ſayd Maiſters of the townes and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (which are deſirous of warre) wylling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determine them ſelues to furniſhe yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto youre Coffers foure Millions of golde, and that thereof they make to you an eſtate as of an yeerely rent, not to ceaſe in their time, for it had neede to be a greate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenue that ſhoulde maynteyne thoſe warres all our life.</p>
               <p>But what anſwere will the aforeſayde maiſters of the townes and Chapters make? me thinkes I heare alreadie what my mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters the <hi>Pariſians</hi> will anſwere: a ſirra, let al alone, for by Saint Iohn we had rather the
<pb facs="tcp:12958:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Hugonots</hi> preached where they liſted, than we would diſburſe ſo much money as ſhould maynteine warres againſt them, and after if in the ende they ſhould get the better hande, they woulde robbe and ſpoyle vs of all that we haue: and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what gaines win we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? And my maiſters of <hi>Lions,</hi> what will they anſwere? Our traffikes (will they ſay) by theſe ciuill warres are decayed, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is left wherewith to ſuſtaine vs, but the ſtockes of our ſhoppes. For ſince the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of thoſe <hi>Hugonots</hi> in this good towne: we haue ſeene nothing elſe but miſerie and hell. There were many good men of them, that loued well the profit of this towne, and therin maynteined ſuch a good trade of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, as the towne was muche the better for, and the merchantes well liked of: and were we not better to ſuffer them with their Religion, than to aduenture the loſſe of all that we haue? They of <hi>Roan, Orleans, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſa,</hi> and all other good townes of Fraunce will anſwere no leſſe. And to be ſhorte, ye ſhall finde few of ſuch courage, but they will ſtoupe to the ſufferance of the exerciſe of the ſayde religion, (both within their townes
<pb facs="tcp:12958:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> and without) to purchaſe peace, for the auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch burthens as the charges of thoſe warres will require. And as for my maſters of the clergie, they will be ſomewhat loth to agree herevnto. Neuertheleſſe, when they ſhall ſee them ſelues driuen to the diſburſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo great ſummes, about a thing the ſucceſſe whereof they ſhall finde doubtfull and incertaine, they will looke better about them. Herewith it may alſo like your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to doe them to vnderſtande, that if they haue ſuch zeale to chaſe this newe Religion, (which they call hereſie) out of the realme of Fraunce, they muſt ſhewe their ſayd zeale, not only in contributing of their money, but alſo in folowing of the warres, by ſeruing in their owne proper perſons.</p>
               <p>The Leuites folowed the warres: and ſo did the Byſhoppes and Prelates of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine. The Cardinall <hi>Fernaſe</hi> went al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo againſt the Proteſtantes, and why, may not the clergie of Fraunce doe the lyke? Set foorth the yong Monkes that are vnder three ſcore yeeres, and let thoſe that be aboue tarie at home to ſay their Maſſes. They will anſwere by the wordes of Dauid, <hi>Zelus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
<pb facs="tcp:12958:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> tuae comedit me. <hi>The zeale of thine houſe hath eaten the vp.</hi>
                  </hi> That is to ſay (ſay they) that the Prieſtes ought to keepe their houſes, but vnder correction, they take that paſſage of the Scripture amiſſe, for to the keeping well of Gods houſe &amp; their own, it behoueth them to paſſe through a number of dangers. Of truth, if theſe good people were but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neare touched with their being ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde in their furnitures, to marche in the warres: their change of countenance would ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne be ſeene. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would ſeeme to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> in lieu of a ſurplis to put on a corſlet, in place of a myter to weare a morio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or burg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner, in ſteade of a croſſe, or an holie water ſprinkle, to bandle a launce, or an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebouſe: where theſe were wont to be mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon mules, to ride vpon barbed horſes or fierce courſers, or elſe to trot on foote: and as they lay erſt vpon their ſoft beds, to lodge now vpon the hard ground (yea and that at the ſigne of the ſtar:) I am wel aſſured, that their only apprehenſion of ſo ſtraunge an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, would driue them to yeelde euen the leauing of their Temples, to the preachers of the Goſpell. Marrie it is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> but that vpon this Marte they would be aſſured, that thoſe preachers nor their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, ſhould be preiudiciall to their goods and reuenues (a poynt verie requiſite to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon.) For they haue good reaſon, not to conſent to the forgoing of their goods, (the ſale of the ſame being to them forbidden vnder the payne of excommunication,) and their reuenues are needefull to their ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life. The wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> that ſendeth vs to the Ante, ſheweth vs (ſay they) that we ought not to ſuffer our Garners to be emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The argument is good: For if the ſmall beaſts (as the Antes) haue ſome care for what to liue by, how muche more for liuing then ought to be the care of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great? This way ſir ſhal not be impertinent, to make the harts of your good ſubiectes, to conſent to the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of peace. And if they refuſe peace, you are by that meanes to enioy their money, wherewith they can no leſſe doe, than furniſh you to the mayntenance of the warres, that make choyce of the ſame: But I verily iudge, they will like beſt of peace, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto moued in reſpecte of their profite and quietneſſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12958:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And this poynt being gayned, that your ſubiectes wil agree to the exerciſe of both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, for the obtaining of peace: all other meanes to bring the ſame to paſſe, ſhall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be compaſſed. For in that the Goſpellers deſire a reformation of iuſtice: the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques and they agree, both feeling it good to haue iuſtice iuſtly adminiſtred. And it ſhuld be very neceſſarie, that a good ſearch and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey through your Parliamentes ſhoulde be made (as well of the higheſt as of the loweſt members thereof,) among whome ſhoulde many be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d napping and faultie, that haue pouled and pilled good men, to their vtter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doings. I meane not the ſifting of the ſame too neare, only the notorious and groſſe offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, (for their offences) are to be touched. And ſuch a ſearch or ſuruey ſhuld be no new thing. We haue of the like many examples. In the time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romane ciuill warres, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Marius, Pompei</hi> and <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> many were diſpoſſeſſed of the Senators eſtate, yea euen by thoſe with whome they tooke part. For euerie of thoſe great conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſought the mean to make many friends in the Senate.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12958:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>But <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> (after he had gotten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goale from his competitours,) was peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably poſſeſſed of the Empire, and had eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed peace amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt his ſubiects: he ſtreight ſought reformation of the ſtates and offices. And a ſpeciall tryall made he of the Senate, as thervnto had ſlipped by vnlawful means, purging the ſame of ſuch vnworthy perſons, and ſo reſtored he it to the auncient beautie and dignitie. <note place="margin">Sueto. in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſto cap. 35.</note> The like (ſir) were needefull in your Parliaments and other places of iuſtice in Fraunce. For the wiſe and good that now be there, ſhall not be grieued, that the corrupt whiche are among them by vnlawfull mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes entred, ſhould be cut off, to the encreaſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honour of ſuch as ſhal remaine. <note place="margin">Treb. Polli in Valeriano.</note> We reade that one of the principall charges of the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of Rome, was the chaſtiſing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing of the vnwiſe and vnworthy Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, which were many times chaſtiſed euen for very ſmall faultes, and what inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience were it, if at this day the office of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure were ſomwhat amnogſt vs brought in vre? Beſides theſe points of the exerciſe of the Euangelicall religion, and reformation of iuſtice: there be many other neceſſarie points
<pb facs="tcp:12958:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the making and perfiting of a good peace: whiche I meane to forbeare heere to touche, as things not expedient. I wyll nowe ſhew the meane howe ſuche a peace may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded vpon and made. For the bringing to paſſe wherof, it ſhoulde me thinkes be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good your Maieſtie dyd as your prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours haue done, when they would yeelde a rule for any good peace of iuſtice or policie to paſſe in Fraunce. Their manner was to put their truſte in certayne perſonages that were faythfull and wyſe, ſuche and: ſo many as myght ſuffiſe, to the bodye of a Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell to any kingly eſtate, for their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the formalities of iuſtice, in the poyntes of right, and in the perticulars that in any policie were to be conſidered of. And if it myght likewiſe pleaſe youre Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit to a dozen (or ſuch other lyke number of perſonages,) the entreatie of all the perticulars of a peace: it ſeemeth to be the onely waye whereby all manner of matters, doubtes, and difficulties, might be decided and reſolued. But it ſhall (ſir) be needefull, that you ſhewe ſo muche fauour to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, as they may nominate one dozen of
<pb facs="tcp:12958:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuch perſons as they ſhall thinke meete (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided that they be good, wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (and apte men) out of the which number, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>way thoſe ſixe to be of the number of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by you ſo to be deputed to entreate of the ſaid matters. And to thoſe twelue (by your ſayde Maieſtie to be choſen) it ſhal be requiſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, that ye giue a ſtrong and large commiſſion, for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all plaintes and griefes, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing &amp; ending of the ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, together with the deciding of all ſuche articles, as ſhall to them by the Goſpellers be preferred, in ſuche manner as may be moſte furthering to the ſayd peace and the common weal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: And that what ſo euer ſhall be ſo determined and agreed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may be of like weight, force and authority, as if your ſelf (ſir) in proper perſon, had decided and accorded it. Which good and large commiſſion, being gyuen to thoſe deputies: it were requiſite that a place of no ſide to be ſuſpected to them, were aſſigned to execute that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion in. As this good town of <hi>Frankford</hi> (myght it pleaſe you to permit their comming thither) is free from all ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, bycauſe bothe the Relygions, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and Euangelike are therin exerciſed,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> yea the verie Iewes haue heere their place of ſafetie, if not here, at <hi>Ausburge,</hi> where both Religions are lykewiſe vſed, or at <hi>Strasbrough</hi> where both parties ſhal be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, or elſe in ſome other good town wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into may be ſafe &amp; ſure acceſſe, as wel for the commiſſioners, as for all ſuche other as ſhall haue with them to doe. The ſayd commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners alſo muſt by your fayde Maieſtie be enioyned (vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine for euer to be baniſhed the realme of Fraunce) not to depart thence, till ſuche time as they haue fully concluded, vpon ſo much as ſhal be neceſſarie, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting of a good perpetuall peace. No more than may the Cardinall from the Conclaue when they thoſe a Pope. Nor the electors of the Empire, when they elect an Emperour. And it behoueth that it be further ordayned, that ſuche of the ſame commiſſioners as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent from the reſt, be bound to yelde forth in writing, the occaſion or reaſon of their ſuche diſſenting, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that if the treatie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through become ineffectuall, as well ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers as thoſe of the french nation, may iudge and knowe, in whome the default doth reſt, that the peace was not concluded, and that
<pb facs="tcp:12958:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> then the reaſons of both parties be to the world put foorth and publiſhed: whereby it may be ſeene who is in the right or wrong, by whiche meane all the worlde ſhall in the end come to iudge of both parties, &amp; ſo iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hate the obſtinate opinion of them, that by the letting of that good peace ſhall tumble <hi>Fraunce</hi> afreſh into the miſeries of warre. And if (by the grace of God) it ſhall happen all the articles to be reſolued, concluded, and agreed vpon, by youre ſayd commiſſioners, and the ſame by both ſortes in two coppies (whereof they of each religion to haue one) to be ſigned: Let it then pleaſe your maieſtie that vnder the name and authoritie of the ſame, it be put foorth in fourme of a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Edict (without altring any iot thereof,) and that the ſame Edict alſo bee ſtabliſhed, ſworne, and confirmed by your ſelfe firſt, in your full priuie counſell, then by all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and other councellours of the ſame, and after by all the generall and perticular e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouernours of prouinces, towns and fortes, &amp; their Lieuetenauntes, by all the Parliamentes, places of Preſidentes, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes, Stewards, and their Liefetenauntes,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:76" rendition="simple:additions"/> with all other your officers: and by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Biſhops, Prelates, Chapiters and Colledges of your Realme. The fourme of which oth alſo to be, that each promiſe, and ſweare before God, and vpon payne of loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their honours, eſtates, offices, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, with the encurring of your diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as infringers of your peace, and vnder the damnation of their ſoules (as muche as in them is) to obſerue and cauſe to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued without fraude or guile, all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the ſayde Edict, nothing therein altered, by way of moderation, declaration, or otherwiſe, other than ſuche declarations and modifications as were made by youre Edict in lyke manner and fourme as was the ſayde Edict of peace. The recordes of which othes, (chiefly thoſe of the Lordes of youre priuie counſell,) the gouernours of prouinces and townes, the Parliamentes, places of preſidentes, and prouinciall eſtates (ioyned to the ſayd Edict) togither, with the actes of publication and eſtabliſhment, to be imprinted: And that the ſayd oth be yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renued, and giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all ſuch, as ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be enſtalled in any office royall, or take
<pb facs="tcp:12958:76" rendition="simple:additions"/> the charge of any other office in the common weale.</p>
               <p>If it might pleaſe your Maieſtie to think good of this platte layde for the bringing to paſſe of a perfect peace to be had in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> mine opinion is, that the Goſpellers woulde well like thereof, and thervnto agree, though they be full (and not without cauſe) of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, ſuſpition, and dread to be deceyued, al things welneere beeing to them ſuſpect. And to prooue that this way carieth with it ſome reaſon, and no whit toucheth the dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of your ſoueraigne authoritie, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience teacheth it to be a thing almoſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie to all Kings and Princes, when they are to deale with any matters of importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, (be it with ſtrangers or others, or when they will make any lawes or ordinaunces tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng iuſtice or pollicie in theyr kingdoms, or countries) to commit the doing thereof to commiſſioners and legates. When the late Kyngs of <hi>Fraunce</hi> youre predeceſſours haue made any good ordinaunces eyther of pollicie, or for the execution of iuſtice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in youre Realme, wherein were contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the formalitie of pleas, the order of
<pb facs="tcp:12958:77" rendition="simple:additions"/> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the maner of making contracts, and many deciſions of rightes taken out of the lawyers hands: it is very certaine, that they were driuen in the ſame to vſe as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries and Legates, their chauncellours, and other meete perſons choſen out of theyr Parliamentes or priuie councels, (for they them ſelues neuer ſtudied in the ſchooles, nor proceeded Doctours of the lawes, Ciuil nor Canon, to the furtheraunce of their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges in the making of ſuch ordinances, but truſted their good and faithful deputies) and authoriſed what their ſaide deputies founde good and profitable for the common wealth, although ſuche reſolutions proceeded not of their owne deuices, neyther did they well vnderſtand the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But when your predeceſſors would cauſe to be ſet downe in writing, the cuſtomes payable within youre countries, they did the ſame by the ſeruice of deputies and legates, and ſuche cuſtomes as were by the ſaide deputies and legates aſſeſſed and written: the Princes by a lawe authoriſed the perpetual payment therof. And when the <hi>Romanes</hi> liked to haue lawes made to rule rightly their common wealth: they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb facs="tcp:12958:77" rendition="simple:additions"/> ten Legates which made a collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the lawes and ordinances that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to them profitable or neceſſary, eyther for the vniuerſall ſtate, or for perticular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities. Whiche ſaid lawes, they placed in twelue tables, and had them in as great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation, as if all the people had made, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided and eſtabliſhed them. For ſeeing they were made by the authoritie and commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuche as then helde the ſoueraigntie, it was al one, as if they them ſelues had made them. When the Emperour <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the ciuill lawes into certayne vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes which he called <hi>Code è digeſte</hi> (gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vſed at this day) he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doing thereof to <hi>Tribonian, Theophile, Dorothe,</hi> and other notable lawyers, for him ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode nothing thereof, as witneſſe the Hiſtoriographers, that ſaye he coulde not reade, ſo is it very certaine that hee neuer vnderſtoode the thouſande part of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters contayned in the ſaide <hi>Code è digeſte.</hi> Yet were thoſe bookes neuertheleſſe by hym aucthoriſed in his allowing of that whiche his commiſſioners by his commaundement did. And it was neuer fayde that thoſe <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:78" rendition="simple:additions"/> people, had done any derogation to their ſouereigntie, in their authoriſing of thoſe ten perſons, to the compoſing of thoſe twelue tables, nor that the Emperour <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> nor youre predeceſſours, did any whit derogate their ſoueraigne authoritie by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting commiſſioners, to make lawes and ordinaunces, that paſſed vnder their princes names and commaundementes, who as it appeareth, alowed of what their deputies ſo by their commiſſions had done. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me thinkes the ſaying may be holden for voyde, that youre maieſtie may not make an Edict of peace by commiſſioners withoute any derogation to youre royall authoritie or ſoueraigntie.</p>
               <p>No more ſhall be any thing againſte the ſame youre giuing to the Goſpellers, the nomination of the ſayde number of perſons, whereout your maieſtie to chooſe the moytie for the ioyning with the like number, by your ſelfe to be named and choſen as legates or deputies for the bringing to paſſe of thys good worke.</p>
               <p>Your predeceſſors haue giuen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to two or three perſons, of their courtes
<pb facs="tcp:12958:78" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Parliaments whom they would to chooſe for them, meete men to ſupplye the offices of Preſidentſhips &amp; counſellours roomes, that were void in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid courtes, as they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo done to Maiors, Conſuls, Shireſes, and other like officers of Townes, for the choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of vnder Baylifes, vnder ſtewardes, &amp; other like petie officers, yet hath it neuer the more bin ſaid, that your ſaide predeceſſors in graunting the ſaide nominations to theyr ſubiects, haue taken ought from their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie royall, which lieth aſmuche in creatyng of magiſtrates, as in making of lawes (as any man of iudgemente maye both ſee and vnderſtand.) The Pope whiche ſaieth hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to haue full power ouer the giftes of benefices, leaueth the nomination of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent not to two or three, but to one, not to princes, but to perticular perſons, whiche commonly in benefiers haue the right of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and the preſenting of ſuch perſons to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, as to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſemeth good, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Pope of any election, but only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtitution: and if by ſuffering of the ſame, he thought any whit to derogate, the ſoueraigne power and authoritie, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:12958:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> he hath ouer the ſaid benefites, he woulde not (I warrant you) permit any ſuch nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So may it playnely be ſeene to youre maieſtie, that your authoritie royall, ſhall no whit bee deminiſhed, by the graunting of your good fauour to the goſpellers in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd nomination.</p>
               <p>Withall is to be conſidered, that it were a thing vnreaſonable (with youre fauour) that all the ſayd Commiſſioners ſhoulde be Catholiques, for by the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the kings your predeceſſours (by all the fourme of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice here and elſe where) and by the lawes deuine, naturall and ciuil, it is lawfull for the partie to accuſe his iudge ſuſpect, be it in matter criminal, or ciuil. And a iudge may be holden for ſuſpect, not only if he be of kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, alied, or Goſſip, a friende to the partie adurrſe, but alſo if he be enemie to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that refuſeth him, or if hee or any of hys kinne haue any intereſt (little or much) in the cauſe, yea if he haue at any time ſhewed hym ſelfe more affectionate on the one ſyde, than on the other, (as he may alſo in diuers other leſſe cauſes of refuſall.) And who is he that ſeeth not, that there is neuer a Catholique
<pb facs="tcp:12958:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> againſt whome theſe poore goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers cannot alledge (not one but) many and ſundry cauſes of recuſation? And if it be thought tollerable to holde a iudge for ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſuſpition to refuſe him in matters of mean weyght: ought he not then to be refuſed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal haue to deale with conſcience, honor, landes, goodes, wiues, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and life?</p>
               <p>And it ought not to ſeeme ſtraunge, that I ſaid it ſhould be meere that the ſaid peace by the ſaid commiſſioners, were entreated of without the Realme, for there be many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that require the ſame. Fyrſt for that it is better (as ſayeth Maſter <hi>Philip de Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> a man wel experimented in the affaires of an eſtate) it ſhoulde be done farre off than meere, and that for diuers conſiderations, namely for the keepyng cloſe of that whyche ſhall from tyme to time be agreed vpon, till all be concluded and finiſhed. For as in a paynted table he that veweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt draught, ſhall finde in the ſame little or nothyng to hys contentment, yet after, the whole work beeing perfited, doth pleaſe him very well: Euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, if during the time of the treatie
<pb facs="tcp:12958:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12958:81" rendition="simple:additions"/> (and before the concluſion of all thynges therein to be argued) ſome peece thereof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vppon ſhoulde bee publiſhed: many were lyke ynough to gayneſay and controll that peace, that vpon the ſight or bearing of the hole reſolution, woulde fynde good cauſe of contentment, bycauſe that he which is not ſatiſfyed in one poynte, may be ſatiſfyed in another. And as the Doctors of the lawe ſay, it ſtandeth not with good reaſon that any ſhould iudge of a lawe or of an Edict, without hauing redde the ſame from the one ende to the other. And as it were a thing very hard to decide or deale with any thyng within the Realme that ſhould not inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent be deuulged<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo the reprehenſions and ſclaunders that would follow ſuche diuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, might be an infallible cauſe that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng ſhoulde bee done, but that entended good worke broken off and laide aſide. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde that, there is no place within youre Realme, but is ſuſpected of the one ſyde or of the other. For the Catholiques will not goe to <hi>Niſmes</hi> nor to <hi>Rochell,</hi> and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers will bee as vnwilling to come at <hi>Paris, Lions, Tholoſa,</hi> or other like place,
<pb facs="tcp:12958:81" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo that for the doing thereof ſuch a place is to be choſen as may be ſure and free for al that ſhall there in haue to doe. And therefore it was that in times paſt when they woulde holde any councill for the examining of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny newe doctrine newly come abroade, for place where the councell ſhoulde be holden, was choſen within the prouince where ſuche doctrine was abroade, or elſe in ſome other ſuch place neere therevnto, as was both ſure and commodious. Therefore was it alſo that by the ordinaunce of your predeceſſors no inqueſt mighte be taken, nor any iuſtice proceede in a place by any of the parties hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſuſpected, as in the houſe of the kinſman, ally, or ſpeciall friend, to him that cauſed the inqueſt to be enpauelled: but an indifferent place therefore by the iudge was to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and by ſhal reaſon may all the townes in Fraunce be ſuſpected: For if the ſuſpition of a place be curiouſly to be looked to and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded in ſmall things: how muche are they to bee looked to in a matter of ſo greate a weight as is the ſeeking and concluding of a peace?</p>
               <p>And where I ſayd it ſhould be meete, that
<pb facs="tcp:12958:82" rendition="simple:additions"/> when the commiſſioners coulde not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vpon ſome articles of the treaty they whiche refuſed to agree and goe through ſhoulde giue out by their writings, the reaſons of their diſſenting and ſtanding aloofe, to the end the worlde mighte ſee who were in the fault: it is not a matter vnreaſonable. For ſuch as ſhall yeeld (as meete is) to the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all things that right and reaſon ſhal finde expedient for the common profit, ſhall not finde it euill, that a reaſon be rendred by them, that otherwiſe, in their paſſions will bee wilfull: and therefore if any refuſe ſo to do, it ſhal ſeeme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they want good wil to ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way that ſhuld bring al things in fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> equitie &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon profit.</p>
               <p>Neyther aught to to be euil taken what I ſpake touching othes. For as the common ſaying is) he that wil wel pay, wil willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become bound: And your maieſty alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by youre ſaide laſt Edict of October ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued this poynt, when ye promiſed in the word of a king, to cauſe to be obſerued what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhould be agreed vpon, and to make the fame paſſe in maner of a recorde, with the conſents of your Parliamentes, towns and commonalties of your realme.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12958:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>I ſhall thinke my ſelfe wel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iffied ſyr), (in all humilitie and reuerence) to haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vnto you (as to my naturall prince) the three poyntes whereof I haue before entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Moſt humbly beſeeching your Maieſtie to take the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in good part as in that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the heartie affection of a good french ſubiect, that wiſheth all encreaſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and proſperitie to your crowne, and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe to your poore ſubiectes. And if it ſhall pleaſe God to moue you to thinke ſo well of this plot (layd for the building of a peace) as you will appoint and charge commiſſioners with the dealing in the ſame I wil ſettle my ſelfe to the opening of ſuche other perticular meanes for the bringing thereof to paſſe, as are not mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e at this preſent in writing to be diſcouered. But amongſt other things, I will open vnto them howe needfull it were that a good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould be made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of <hi>Machi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> for euer out of Fraunce, as one that hath bene the greateſt lyar, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture that euer was in the World, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Romanes, Greekes, and Frenchmen, and all other well ruled commonwealthes, hauing bin ruled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leane contrarie to his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.
<pb facs="tcp:12958:83" rendition="simple:additions"/> And that his diſciples whiche haue brought into Fraunce the obſeruation of his precepts, haue bene the very cauſe of the ciuill warres and miſeries of the realme. It may be that his precepts be good and neceſſarie for thoſe of his nation, for they reach (among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things) the nonmaking of account of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny religion, otherwiſe than for the keping of the people in a ſuperſtitious feare and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: vpon which his opinion might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that the Turkiſh religion (wherefrom God deliuer vs) might ſafely of any be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, for by the ſame the Turks holdeth his ſubiectes vnder ſuche feare and obedience, as they refuſe not at his commaundement the murthering of them ſelues, thinking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon to flee ſtraight to their Paradiſe, that floweth with mylke and hony. He ſheweth alſo, that a Prince ſhould beare good counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to all promiſe muche, and keepe touche in nothing, more than ſire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th to his aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Moreouer, his diſciples vſe theſe faire perſuaſions. If it be profitable to a Kyng (ſay they) to tooke out and deſtroy ſuch hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſuch olde him doe it, without taking any aduiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what may folowe of his ſo
<pb facs="tcp:12958:83" rendition="simple:additions"/> doing. Such as haue brought into Fraunce the obſeruation of <hi>Machiauels</hi> precepts, haue not well conſidered, that the Frenchmen in nature farre differ from their nation. The French are naturally religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, louers of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and take no pleaſure neyther in falſify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their fayth, contemning of their honor and reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor in the ſheading of bloud. If the <hi>Macheuilians</hi> be endued with thoſe good qualities: let them there kepe them, and folowe their Doctors doctrine, that was the greateſt <hi>Atheiſt</hi> that euer the worlde bred, with his companion the <hi>Aretine,</hi> as their writings doth openly ſhew, ſo as they keepe them ſelues from poyſoning of our Frenche nation, with thoſe their abhominable vices. But I will reſerue till another time (when it ſhall better fall out to the purpoſe) the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king more largely to my Lords &amp; Maiſters the <hi>Macheuilians,</hi> whome I will then ſhew, that al their policie &amp; ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, is none other than a brutiſh ignorance, accompanyed with a wicked heart and will: and that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer read the good hiſtories writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Greeke, Latin, or Frenche, or if they haue read, they neuer well vnderſtoode them. I will for this
<pb facs="tcp:12958:84" rendition="simple:additions"/> time proceede no further, but make an end of this preſent declaration, the which I once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine moſt humbly beſeech your Maieſtie to take in good part, ſo as it may paſſe from this good towne of <hi>Frankford</hi> to your handes. Praying the Creatour of all things, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due you with his grace, ſhortly to eſtabliſh a good peace in your poore Realme, ſo muche torne and ſpoyled by theſe warres paſte, by meane whereof, all your ſubiectes may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto you their good and willing obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. The ſame alſo preſerue you in happy proſperitie, and encreaſe you with much power and honour.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12958:84"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
